<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Annus Sophiæ jubilæus, The sophick constitution, or, The evil customs of the world reform'd a dialogue between a philadept and a citizen concerning the possibility of the sophick transmutation, the probability that there are adepts in the world ... : to which is added, A summary of some conferences with an artist, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13049626</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13049626</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25483)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 406:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Annus Sophiæ jubilæus, The sophick constitution, or, The evil customs of the world reform'd a dialogue between a philadept and a citizen concerning the possibility of the sophick transmutation, the probability that there are adepts in the world ... : to which is added, A summary of some conferences with an artist, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 72, [4], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes advertisements.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alchemy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96950:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Annus Sophiae Jubilaeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sophick CONSTITUTION: OR, THE Evil Cuſtoms of the World Reform'd.</p>
            <p>A DIALOGUE, Between a <hi>Philadept</hi> and a <hi>Citizen;</hi> CONCERNING The Poſſibility of the Sophick Tranſmutation; The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability that there are Adepts in the World; And, in that Caſe, the Duties of Adepts and other Men to each other, and the <hi>Advantages</hi> that would accrue from the Obſervation of thoſe Duties.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A Summary of ſome Conferences with an Artiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Leſt I come, and ſmite the Earth with a Curſe.</l>
               <l>The crooked Paths ſhall be made ſtraight.</l>
               <l>Ye have not, becauſe ye ask not. Ye ask, and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs, that ye may conſume it upon your Luſts.</l>
               <l>Why, even of your ſelves, judge ye not what is right?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> Inn in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96950:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96950:2"/>
                  <head>Advertiſement.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Papers were ready for the Preſs, in the beginning of this Year, One Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Seven Hundred; that is the Reaſon they are intituled <hi>Annus Jubilaeus.</hi> It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſome will ask me, Where is the <hi>Cui bono</hi> of this Dialogue? You ſay expreſly you are no Adept, and conſequently you cannot deſign, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to lay the Foundation of a Negotiation: Do you write then for the Adepts ſake, in caſe there be ſuch Men; or is your aim to perſuade them to communicate themſelves to you, tho' often you appear not to be fully perſuaded, your ſelf, that there is ſuch a Thing as the Philoſophers Stone; or perhaps, believing it to be a mere Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do you only ſeek to inſtruct the World, to propoſe what you fancy might be Reform'd to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Happineſs of Mankind, and do you eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay hereby to put Men upon doing Acts of Love and Charity towards one another? I anſwer, There is ſomething of all this; theſe Queſtions touch the ſeveral ends I have, at ſeveral times, propoſed to my ſelf in this Writing: Howbeit my chiefeſt deſire is, that it be not uſeleſs to my Brethren, the promoting of whoſe Felicity I ſhall have the advantage to have endeavoured, whatever the ſucceſs of it may be, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality
<pb facs="tcp:96950:3"/>of Men being partial and ſelfiſh, and captivated by their Paſſions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Heads of the Regulations to be conſidered of, in caſe Adepts were invited by a Prince and State.</head>
                     <item>I. Touching Adepts.</item>
                     <item>II. Touching Religion.</item>
                     <item>III. Touching Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                     <item>IV. Touching Subſidies, and Proviſions for the ſecurity of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
                     <item>V. Touching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors Duty of tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an equal care of all the Subjects in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</item>
                     <item>VI. Touching Law and Phyſick.</item>
                     <item>VII. Touching Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                     <item>VIII. Touching Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Education.</item>
                     <item>IX. Touching the way and manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for the Poor.</item>
                     <item>X. Touching Order and Policy in Cities, Buildings and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; Touching the improving the State and Riches of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, preventing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Expences and Vanities, and Reforming all evil Cuſtoms.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96950:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Annus Sophiae Jubilaeus.</hi> The Sophick CONSTITUTION: OR, The Evil Cuſtoms of the World Reform'd. A DIALOGUE, Between a <hi>Philadept</hi> and a <hi>Citizen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
                     <p>GOod morrow t'ye, <hi>Phil.</hi> What News from the Adepts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philadept.</speaker>
                     <p>A good morning to you, Sir: You would be much ſurprized ſtill, I find, if, after all, I ſhewed you in Adept.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſs, you'd do more than I expect.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96950:4"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>But why ſhould you think that impoſſible?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>And why ſhould you even think it credible that there is ſuch an Art, as that pretended one of the Tranſmutation of Metals?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>The Principles of it ſeem to be rational.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>How, I pray thee? Why may not I as well traſmute Marble or Alablaſter into Silver, as Braſs or Copper into Gold?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>The difference is very great. All Metals are of the ſame kind, and differ only in ſome accidental Qualities, which being remov'd they become equally pure, having all a metallick Mercury, Salt and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, ſome only being more crude than others, or having contracted ſome external Impurities in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Matrixes of the Earth: So that Tranſmuting of Metals is not ſuch a wonder as at firſt we are apt to imagine; 'tis not changing a Nature into another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; it is only ſeparating Impurities and Digeſting, and then the crude is concocted, and the impure is as the moſt pure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But which way muſt the Impurities of Metals be purged, and their Crudities digeſted; or how do you know, after all, that this will cauſe a perfect Tranſmutation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>If the Crudities be digeſted and the Impurities purged, there can remain but a perfect metallick Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, Salt and Mercury; more than which there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in any perfect metallick Subject whatſoever, only there may be ſeveral degrees of Purification and Concoction: But the way how to effect that, is ſecret, and is that which muſt be ſought out; Philoſophers ſay it is altogether to be done with one thing, that is, Fire, as you may ſee in their Writings, to which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I refer you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank ye heartily, <hi>Phil.</hi> I deſign not to break my Head with their caballiſtical Cant, their unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible, and ſenſeleſs Fuſtion. I had rather make an
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96950:4"/>honeſt Fellow of thee, and perſwade you to rail at all Chymiſts, and burn their Books. For, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the plauſible Story of purifying and concoct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Tranſmutation of Metals is (for ought I ſee) an imaginary thing, and moſt credibly, nothing like it was ever known: Conclude therefore an Adept's an Aſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>An Adept is one that can change baſe Metals into the moſt perfect Silver and Gold. He can't be an Aſs, that doth this. And why ſhould you think it improbable, that there ſhould be ſome Men that can do it, ſeeing you grant that the Principles of the Art are plauſible? It is more likely that if it be poſſible to be done, ſome Men before now, thro' God's Bleſſing, have found it out. You ſee daily by experience, that Soap and Water cleanſe a foul Cloth, and that Ink dieth it through and through: The Water of the Adepts is Fire; and Fire is their Soap, and their Tincture. If all theſe Reaſons won't move you, I'll tell you that ſome Men have been known to have done extraordinary Cures. I my ſelf have known ſome that could draw Gold out of Silver, and Silver out of Lead. Now if theſe extraordinary things may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, why ſhould the other be more impoſſible?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>They cannot be thought impoſſible by you, if you have actually known ſome Adept.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>I never ſaw, my ſelf, any Man, that I know of, who could tranſmute the baſe into perfect Metals: But I doubt not there are ſome that are living, who in all probability have.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>If there were ſuch Men indeed as Adepts, how could it come to paſs that we were acquainted with none of them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>If Adepts had been publickly known, they would have been in danger, thro' the wickedneſs of Men. But had not Men rendered themſelves uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Communication of Adepts, how happy would the World have been?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96950:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't fully underſtand what you'd expect from Adepts, but I'd fain hear what you think Men obliged to do, to qualify themſelves for the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the Sophi. Would you have us, full of good Nature and Credulity, expoſe our ſelves to the Cheats of every Alchymiſt, and as ſoon as any one ſets up for a Philoſopher, receive him into our Houſes, and allow him no ſmall ſhare of our Eſtates?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>There is ſcarce any Perſon more undeſerving, or more to be deſpiſed and abhorred, than a Cheat in general, and particularly in Chymiſtry, where Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Gold are promiſed, when the Impoſtor is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he has no reaſon to hope any thing from the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick Philoſophy, but what he can get from other Men by his Lying and Impudence, and his vaſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which himſelf ſees no ground for. On the other hand, there are no Perſons that deſerve more to be eſteem'd and every ways to be reſpected, than thoſe whom God has choſen to impart to them the higheſt Secrets of Nature. They are the <hi>Adepti,</hi> the Elect, thoſe who have <hi>obtained</hi> the moſt ſingular Favour, whom God <hi>takes</hi> for His particular Servants and Friends, and whom He entruſts with the greateſt Riches and Health, and with the Tree of Life it ſelf, that is, the uſe of it <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> 'till he think fit to tranſlate them to a better Place, to which they aſpire. Betwixt thoſe two ſorts of Men there are others of whom there may be ſome good, and ſomebad, tho' not ſo good or ſo bad as either of the former; they are thoſe who profeſs to ſtudy the Writings of the Adeptiſts, but not to be certain of the Art, are willing to ſearch after it to the beſt of their Power, but have not all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies neceſſary to that end, and therefore deſire the help and aſſiſtance of thoſe that are able to give it. Theſe may be termed the <hi>Mercenary Candidates</hi> of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimy, to diſtinguiſh them from thoſe that ſeek the Art by themſelves and at their own Charge. Now theſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96950:5"/>three ſorts of Chymiſts deſerve to be treated very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhould be done, do you think, to the Impoſtors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>They ought to be ſeverely puniſhed by the Laws, as Cheats and Robbers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>And how are they to be known from other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>They muſt be tried by their Works, as other Malefactors. I have heard of one who frequented a Bookſeller's Shop, where ſome Chymical Books were ſold. A certain Perſon coming to buy one of thoſe Books, the Impoſtor fixes his Eyes upon him, and looks as if he were in an extaſie; preſently after fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth him, tells him, he has found him to be the Man to whom he might diſcover himſelf, aſſures him that by infallible Experience, he is certain of being Maſter of the Art; in ſhort, after ſome interviews, makes propoſal of borrowing Mony for the Work, but in fine was diſcovered to have made the ſame Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o other Men, to have drawn conſiderable Sums from them, from thence forth to have come at them no more, and to have ſpent the Mony, not in an Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratory, but in lewd Houſes, and with lewd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions. Hanging is not too ſevere a Puniſhment for ſuch Wretches.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What Treatment deſerve your Mercenary Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>If it be uncertain whether they be honeſt Men, or Deceivers, Men cannot be too wary, leſt they be impoſed upon by them; there cannot be too much Circumſpection uſed in this Caſe. However, they ought not to be affronted or injured, in the mean time, as long as it is not evident that they have baſe Deſigns; for that were the higheſt unjuſtice, and would be to run the hazard of wronging innocent Perſons, and Perſons perhaps moſt particularly acceptable to God. When
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96950:6"/>it appears that they are wicked Men, who have no other deſign than to deceive others, their Addreſſes ought to be rejected with Scorn and juſt Anger, and other Men ought to be warned from them. But if it be credible that they mean well, and that they are not unqualified for the Art, thoſe that have ſome faith in it, and can, without hurting themſelves, venture ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing towards the obtaining of it, may do as they find themſelves diſpoſed. It is poſſible that the Mony may be well beſtowed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But how ſhall it be known, who are thoſe that do not mean well, or thoſe that are qualified for the Art?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>They may be known by their Works, by their Propoſals, and by their Skill. Any Man that has a Genius this way, may gueſs whether the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders have a Taſte of the Art, and are likely to make any Progreſs and Diſcoveries in it. Deceivers run upon Whimſies, work out of kind, upon unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Subjects, and offer Violence to Reaſon and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to the Writings of generally approved Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. Then their very Addreſſes and Propoſitions are unphiloſophical. They do not care whom they deal with, ſo they can but get by them. And if you do but give them good Wages for the preſent, they make no Conditions about the management of the Elixir, in caſe it ſhould be attained unto; they leave that at your diſpoſal, they make you wholly Maſter of it, they yield to you all their Pretentions as to that, you may make them what ſhare, and you may make what uſe of it you pleaſe. But true Men, who really think they have ſome Skill, and who ſincerely fear God, are moſt nice as to this point. So they but ſettle this as it ought to be, they are ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and will not be ſo exact and intereſſed as to the other Conditions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96950:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>In the <hi>Eſſay concerning Adepts,</hi> which you ſhewed me, 50 <hi>l.</hi> a year Wages is propoſed, and 30 <hi>l.</hi> for Board; which is a pretty ſophical Sum.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>That's a Propoſal for noble Perſons, as it is there ſaid, (<hi>P.</hi> 48.) but ſuch Wages are Arbitrary, and as for the reckoning of 30 <hi>l.</hi> for Board, that was to put Things to the utmoſt, and it was alſo in part occaſioned from the accounting of a Domeſtick's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, by a Perſon of Quality, giving 15 <hi>l.</hi> Wages, and reckoning the Board 30 <hi>l.</hi> a year. Howbeit, well qualified Artiſts will not deſire unreaſonable Terms: I have heard of one who offered to ſome Perſons (for whom he had a great eſteem) to make this Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to accept of 60 <hi>l.</hi> a year, in all, for Board and Penſion, and lay down an Employment of 120 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> to give himſelf wholly to that Work. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred kindneſs was not accepted of, yet the like Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers poſſibly will not always be to be had. But that's off of the buſineſs. To return; It is certain that to accompliſh this Art, as <hi>Geber</hi> obſerved, ſome Charges are neceſſary, eſpecially for a good ſetting up, to have Things convenient; and it is indiſpenſibly neceſſary to have a Workman very ſtrong and healthful of Body: Now it is poſſible that he that has exactly the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, has not ſufficiently theſe outward Neceſſaries, without which, tho' he do what he can, he will not be able to obtain the deſired end; wherefore an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt may need Aſſiſtance. But Artiſts who have ſome hopes, and ſee ſome probability of Succeſs, in time, (tho' then they want Means to make neceſſary Trials) will be very careful whom they deal with, and upon what Conditions, as touching the uſe and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Elixir, in caſe it ſhould ever be got. They will not leave it in their Partner's Power to abuſe ſo great a Treaſure; and to the Signing of Covenants, they will require the Confirmation of the moſt ſacred Oaths.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96950:7"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Some Gentlemen would not like ſo many Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations; or elſe would laugh at them, when made.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>The more's the pity. Such Perſons ſhould not be dealt with. Skilful Artiſts, if they fear God, will make a conſcience of having any thing to do with them. And certainly to obſerve the Cautions that are neceſſary, the fureſt way is that it be ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that thoſe whom a skilful Artiſt covenants with, may know and ſee nothing of what ſhall be done, they being only, by Agreement and Oath, to have a certain Portion of tranſmuted Metal, in caſe of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the laſt thing, by which thoſe may be known, who are qualified for the Philoſopher's work?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>A good Life and Converſation. Philoſophers cannot be expected to be abſolutely free from all failings, no more than the beſt Men; but they muſt be free from all evil Habits, elſe the Bleſſing of God can never be thought to attend them, and without God's ſpecial Grace 'tis in vain to hope for Succeſs in this Art.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>You'd give a great Idea of it. What to think of the matter, I don't well know. But to follow the thread of our Diſcourſe, what Treatment do you eſteem is due to Adepts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>There are divers ſorts of Adepts, and divers ſorts of Men whom Adepts may have to do with.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold; theſe Diſtinctions will carry you far, and, I preſume, to little purpoſe, unleſs you reſolve one Queſtion: Pray, how ſhall theſe Adepts be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known? By what you have given me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, they won't be ſo complaiſant as to teach one preſently their Art; nay, 'tis great odds if they will have ſo much confidence in a Man, as to truſt him with a little of their Powder. Muſt we then believe 'em upon their word?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96950:7"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>I would have ſatisfied you on that Point in due time; and what I was ſaying was neceſſary in order to that, as you ſhall ſee. In general, Adepts will not at all communicate themſelves unleſs it be to Men of known probity, and on whoſe Fidelity and Diſcretion they may rely: But to convince them of what they are, they will not ſcruple to let them ſee ſomething of that which they can do; to make Projection before them, —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank ye, <hi>Phil.</hi> As for their ſhewing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, I would not give them a Button for that. Don't I know that your falſe Crucibles with double bottoms, your hollow Coals, your iron Rods with Gold at the end of 'em, your golden Lead, and the like, will make red Precipitate paſs for the Stone, and Impoſtors for Adepts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Not if you chuſe your Lead, make uſe of your own Coals, provide the Crucibles and all the Utenſils your ſelf, and make the Projection with your own Hands, the Adept too being at a diſtance: But if he be under reſtraint from communicating the Powder, he may put into another Body's Hands the Gold made by the Powder, which all Goldſmiths will know from the Natural, it being much finer; and he may produce an imperfect kind of Gold, white or red, which is exactly of the Nature of other Gold, (ſave that it will not ſo eaſily melt,) and which none but true Adepts can make: And if he be an Adept of the higher rank, he may work wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cures in a very little time. For, as I ſaid, there are ſeveral ſorts of Adepts, ſome knowing more than others, and ſome really knowing all the parts of the Art, but not having actually wrought all as yet with their Hands, tho' having done enough to be termed Sophi.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Well; and what are the ſeveral kinds of Men, that Adepts may communicate themſelves to? Rich
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96950:8"/>or Poor, thoſe of the Commonality or Nobility, ſuch as are in Power, or that have no Power?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>None of theſe ſeveral ranks of Men are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the poſſibility of having the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Adepts. Now if you will give me leave to put the Queſtion to you, What Treatment do you, your ſelf, think ſhould be due from theſe ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Adeptiſts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't well know what are the Obligations of other Men to the Sophi; but to ſpeak ſincerely, I am apt to believe that moſt People would make it their only buſineſs to get what they could out of them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>O World! wretched, wicked World! when will you ceaſe to make good Men miſerable, and to be the Authors of your own miſery? Keep your ſelves private ſtill, my Reverend Fathers, and moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friends! The Hour's not yet come. <hi>Propter Peccata, tardantur munera grata.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But yet, I pray you, what do you think requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>That Men would religiouſly conſider of it, put themſelves in the Adepts room, and deal towards them, as they would that other Men ſhould deal towards themſelves, if themſelves were Adepts. They ſhould conſider that Adepts are Perſons dear to God, His particular Favorites; That they are the Men of God, and Men after God's own Heart, that ſeek not their own Glory, and that have no eſteem, for the Vanities of this World, but whoſe chief aim and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is the Glory of God, and the Good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: That therefore they ought to be reſpected, loved, and aſſiſted; That they ought to be look'd upon as the Embaſſadors, and Commiſſioners of God; That their Perſon is ſacred; That then they ought to be protected and deſended by all that know them, and that their Endeavours for the good of Men ought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96950:8"/>to be furthered and encouraged. The Poor ſhould be glad to do them what Service they could, to be of ſome uſe to promote the Happineſs of the World. The Rich ſhould make an Offering of their Power and Riches to the Glory of God, and eſteem that their greateſt Happineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But ſhould Adepts do nothing for their Friends and Benefactors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>We may ſpeak of that, by and by: Adepts know their Duty, and will not be wanting on their part.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>However, we ſhould be glad to know what they judge to be their part. But now I think of it, there is one doubt I would have reſolved. You have intimated that rich Men ſhould aſſiſt Adepts with their Riches; but how can Adepts ſtand in need of ſuch an Aſſiſtance, if it be true that they have the Art to make as much Gold as they pleaſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>They may be Adepts, and not have brought yet their Powder to that Multiplication, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make great quantities of Gold. And 'tis not enough to have Gold, it muſt be changed for current Coin: Now rich Men may do that, getting it minted for the Adept, and if they fear and love God, they ought to do it. And when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that a Perſon, whom they know, is an Adept, but has not brought yet the Stone to its Perfection, they ought to offer him all the Aſſiſtance and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they are capable of, even their own Houſes, and Eſtates, and to be themſelves their Agents, and their Guards; and all this for the ſake of God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I'd make my Conditions firſt, I think, and would not ſtand to a Chymiſt his Courteſie. For every Penny I'd have a Pound.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you'd do all for your ſelf, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for God; and the Adept might be recalled, before he had ſo much as provided for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96950:9"/>Subſiſtence of his Friends, or done any publick Good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But how ſhould I know an Embrio-Adept, or an Infant-Sophi, that has not Gold enough yet for his own occaſions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>By the ſame ſigns that I have told you Adepts may be known in general. For if he be a true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Adept, as you call him, he may do, at leaſt, in ſome ſmall meaſure, what other Adepts do; for he cannot at all be denominated an Adeptiſt, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not produce pure Gold made by Alchimy, and the imperfect Gold I have ſpoken of before; and in ſome time, he may be able to work ſome Cures.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I would live for ever, if I knew an Adeptiſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>You muſt deſire to live for ever in Heaven. That's the only Seat of perfect, undiſturbed, and laſting Happineſs. God will have all wiſe Men withdraw their Affections from this World, and fit themſelves for a better Place. It is appointed for all Men once to die. Adepts will not deſtroy the Order of Nature. And if any reſiſted the Sentence, God, in anger, would force them to ſubmit to it, againſt their Wills, and would for ever drive them out of Paradice, and exclude them from his Reſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What advantage then ſhould one reap, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Adept?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>The advantage of doing Good, or at leaſt of endeavouring it, and being an example to the World.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>For my part, if I were an Adept, and could make as much Gold as I pleaſed, I'd do good to my ſelf in the firſt place, and then to my Friends.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>That were not unlawful, but we muſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate God, and do good to all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Before I thought of any Body elſe, to tell you the Truth, I'd do my own Buſineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96950:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>And what would you do for your ſelf?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould conſider of that. But what do you think, your ſelf, that other Men would do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Many would do fooliſh Things, and Things diſagreeable to God. But, alaſs, remember you not the weighty Queſtion put by our Saviour: <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man, if he gain</hi> (♂) <hi>the whole World, and loſe his own Soul?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But could I not, without loſing my Soul, go, for inſtance, to a Prince, in caſe I were an Adept, and propoſe to him to give him a ſhare of my Treaſures, if he'd make me Partner with him, of his Dignity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>No Adept would ever do that. Adepts in being the Friends of God, are above all Human Glory, and it would be a ſin in them, who know the full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and obligations of Vertue, to accept of worldly Honour: It is their indiſpenſible Duty, to refuſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that is accompanied with Vanity and Pride, Pomp and Oſtentation, and that ſeems, in the leaſt, to trample under foot our fellow Creatures, as if we were of an other Make than they. If Adepts forgot themſelves, God would puniſh them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But ſuppoſe I were originally poor, and now had the Art to make Gold, could not I, at leaſt, addreſs my ſelf to ſome rich Man to exchange a great quantity of my Gold, without danger, and at little loſs, and put my ſelf in a Capacity of enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Family, and making a good Figure in the World?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Adepts will not make a Figure in the World. If an Adept left a Hundred a Year, with a good Calling, to every one of his Children, he would reckon to have made a moſt plentiful Proviſion for his Family.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>A Calling! what; ſhould my Children learn a Trade?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96950:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Adepts will not bring up their Children to do nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What need my Children work? If I were an Adept, could not I leave 'em the Art?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>The Art muſt not be communicated, for love or kindred, but purely for vertue-ſake: He that is indubitably qualified for it, let him have it, under the philoſophical Seal; but it muſt not be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to many.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſhould I know, who is qualified for the Art?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>If he be a vertuous, religious, conſcientious Perſon, that fears and loves God, that habitually li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth well, that delights to do good, that has a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Affection for his fellow Creatures, that deſpiſes Luxury and Vanity, that abhors Injuſtice and all manner of Vice, that loves Temperance, Mediocrity and Simplicity of Life, that is zealous for the Glory of God and the Good of Men, that ſeeks not world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Honour, that can keep a Secret, and that will bind himſelf by the moſt ſacred and ſolemn Oaths not to make an ill uſe of the Elixir; he is well quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Alaſs; where ſhall ſuch a one be found?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>'Till he be found, and be certainly known to be ſuch, the Art muſt not be revealed. There is no going haſtily, and then repenting, in a Buſineſs of this Nature. The Adept muſt be able to give a good account of his Truſt to Almighty God, or elſe be for ever reprobated: If he lightly, and for any reaſons whatſoever, diſcover the Art to an unworthy Friend, that ſhall make a bad uſe of it, he muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for all the miſcarriages of his wicked Diſciple, who poſſibly may make the greateſt part of Men mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, thro' his Avarice, Ambition and Haughtineſs, and oppreſs religious and conſcientious Perſons. It would be even difficult enough to find a rich Man
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96950:10"/>ſo vertuous, whom an Adept could truſt for the Dealings he ſhould have with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſo? If you or I knew an Adept, could not we go to ſome rich Man, of good Repute, to make Terms with him, obtain particularly a ſolemn Promiſe of his Protection, and require the moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Confirmations to the ſaid Terms? And could not the Adept afterwards, treat ſafely in Perſon?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe things are eaſie in the Speculation: All the difficulty is when they come to be put in Practice. Not but that there may be ſome rich Men that are good and vertuous, and capable to keep a Secret, if Adepts knew them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But muſt nothing be ventured? You know the Proverb. Would it be better for Adepts always to lie cloſe, and live by themſelves, like Owls? Would it not be more noble and generous for them, to help an illuſtrious and heroick, a magnanimous, vertuous and charitable Prince, the Father of his People, the Deliverer of Nations, the Refuge of the Diſtreſſed, the Reſtorer of Religion, the Defender of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah, Sir, would to God, he were, in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Bounty, pleaſed, if there are Adepts in the World, to ſend ſome of them to this great and good Prince! But theſe Deliberations muſt come from God, and not from Men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, <hi>Phil.</hi> God will not be againſt good Purpoſes, that tend to his Glory, and the good of Men. What other end is it credible that ſuch a Prince can propoſe to himſelf?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>It is true: And I heartily wiſh that if there are ſuch Men as Adepts, they would ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it. But I believe God's Providence muſt be concerned herein, in a moſt particular manner; and if the beſt Man came, without it, to enjoy any of the Advantages of the Elixir, God might confound
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96950:11"/>the beſt Deſigns, and give the Men over to divers Temptations and Miſeries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, <hi>Phil.</hi> you ſay you fear God, and real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh the Happineſs of the World, and the general good of Mankind: If it be ſo, and if you were an Adept, ſhould not you take hold of all Opportunities to do good?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe things do not concern us; and Adepts, no doubt, underſtand them better than we.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>For my part, I can ſcarce be brought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve firmly that there are Adepts, for theſe two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: Firſt, Becauſe it is ſaid, That if there are Adepts, they muſt be good Men, and ſurely good Men would not live in the World without doing good according to their Capacity. Secondly, It is not likely that Men that could make Gold ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly lie hid, and thereby deny themſelves all the Comforts of Life. I might add, that we ſee no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of this Gold-making Trade; for, firſt or laſt, we ſhould have had ſome demonſtration of it, and we ſhould ſee Gold more plentiful than it is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>What you ſay you might add to your two Reaſons, may be compriſed in and anſwered with the firſt. It is Men's Faults, and not the Adepts, if Adepts cannot communicate themſelves with full ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and aſſurance that they ſhall be always Maſters of their Liberty and Elixir, ſhall do no more with it than they pleaſe, and ſhall put it to no other uſe than ſuch as they like. And this very thing anſwers your ſecond Reaſon; for ſhall Adeps, for the Pleaſures of this Life, run the hazard of doing more than they can anſwer to God? Alaſs, Adepts care little for the Enjoyments of this World, tho' they be ſubject to Paſſions like other Men. They have other Comforts than thoſe the World can give. Being, as it were, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Croſs in moſt parts of the Earth, they are wholly intent on a better State. Beſides, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96950:11"/>beſt of ſimplicity of Life. An Adept will not have rich Cloths, Furniture and Equipage, nor will accept of Titles, or Honour; thoſe Things, and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy are inconſiſtent: He looks upon all Men as being equal and Brethren, and upon himſelf as no better than others; he would not have others reſpect him, more than he would reſpect them: As for Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Dignities, he looks upon them, as Things very dangerous, and not eaſily reconcileable with Chriſtian Humility; he would have all Men go plain, even plainer than the Quakers, and <hi>Thou</hi> one another without vain Appellation, and not uſe the vanity of Salutes, nor deſire the vain honour of being ſaluted, and be thereby diſtinguiſhed from poor Men, who by that means are humbled and afflicted, ſeeing themſelves abaſed and deſpiſed. It were well, if there was not ſuch reſpect of Perſons; and if thoſe that are in Office, and have ſome Degrees and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities above others, were content to be well ſerved and obeyed. That would be more Chriſtian-like, and it is certain it would be ſufficient. The Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination is very well preſerved among the Turks, and among the Quakers, who uſe no Ceremonies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>You amaze me!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Look ye; it is very credible that this is the Senſe of the Adepts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>How comes it to paſs, then, that you conform not to it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not in Circumſtances to do ſo, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other Men that would not approve of it. I believe ſomething may be done for Peace-ſake, the chief Eſſentials of Religion being retained in general, and the great Duties of Juſtice, Moderation and Charity, being witneſſed unto, and profeſſed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>You are one of the anointed and inſpired! I warrant, you don't allow the uſe of the Sacraments!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96950:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea, and believe their neceſſity too. I am no Quaker. But I love that which is good, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I find it; and would force no Body to do any thing againſt his Conſcience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you believe it unlawful to make War?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Not when it is for the Defence and Security of a People.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you think it a ſin to govern Men?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Far from that, <hi>I</hi> eſteem it the higheſt Vertue to do it well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then, would you not accept of ſome Government, if it were lawfully offered you? What! If the Kings of <hi>Sweeden</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> for inſtance, were willing to aſſociate you to them, or if ſome Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick would put her ſelf under your Protection, and make you their Sovereign, would you refuſe them if you were an Adept?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>An Adept, as I ſaid before, muſt refuſe all vain Glory, all worldly Honour, all Pomp and Oſtentation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But he ſhould take hold of fair Opportunities of doing univerſal good. He might, if you will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe all perſonal Honour, all Ceremonies, and pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Attendance, keep himſelf as private as he could deſire, and ſee none but thoſe he had Buſineſs with, and whom he would ſend for; never eat in Publick, nor with any Company, if he did not like it, much leſs with any manner of Pomp, wave all pompous Stile, and be diſtinguiſh'd only by ſome modeſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as <hi>The Commiſſary General,</hi> or the like, be called barely by his own name, anſwer to no Body that did not <hi>Thou</hi> him, nor admit any that pulled off the Hat in his Preſence, not ſuffer his Hand to be kiſſed, nor the knee to be bowed before him, and ſtipulate that he might be as plain as he would, <hi>Thou</hi> every Body, and uſe no Ceremonies: All this might be granted, and then why ſhould he not accept a part in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96950:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>This were poſſible, perhaps, if Adepts would accept of Power, as it is credible they would never do; They are not like other Men; They are not ambitious; They wonder that Princes ſhould fight to enlarge their Sovereignties; They look upon Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as a trouble, and trouble is not naturally deſired; They eſteem therefore that none can be willing to take it upon them, except Men would be governed well, and ſuffer all ill Cuſtoms to be reformed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't know how far this Reformation ſhould go, nor conſequently how far it would be acceptable to the Governed. I thought an Adept would have had nothing to think of, but to make Endowments for Hoſpitals, Schools and Colledges, and the like. However, there might be this Expedient to make all well, in caſe an Adept, and a Nation ſhould grow weary of one another; the Adept might be quietly and peaceably diſcharged, and return to a private Life, and let the Nation govern it ſelf as it would. For my part, were I a Sophi-Emperor, I would buſie my ſelf only to do what good might eaſily be done, and I'd take all innocent Pleaſure. I would make Proviſion for the Poor, the Lame, the Blind, for Children, Widows and old People; and to recreate my ſelf after Buſineſs; I would have the fineſt Walks, and Gardens in the Univerſe; I ſhould alſo delight in ſeeing Soldiers diſciplined, and in having a great number of Guards, the choiceſt Men in the World.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>An Adept would think it unworthy of him to provide himſelf Guards. If he keep himſelf private, he need none. If he governed, as you ſuppoſe, his People might look to him, if they thought him worth their guarding: If any miſchance happened him, they would be the moſt puniſhed, and the greateſt loſers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>You'd have all People be exact in their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; but what if they did not do their Duty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96950:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>They ſhould anſwer it to God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>True; but I'd do what I could, that they ſhould anſwer it alſo to the Laws. For a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Men are moved only by preſent Rewards or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>There's nothing indeed more to be deſired, than that all juſt and rational Laws were the Meaſure of Men's Actions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>They ought certainly to be ſo. Pray, then, ſuppoſe you were an Adept, and were invited, as I ſaid, to ſome ſhare of Government, what Cuſtoms would you reform, what Laws would you deſire to be enacted, what Conditions would you have?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>That would require a mature Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But what do you now think?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>To tell you all that ſhould come in my Thoughts, concerning what might poſſibly be reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the World, would carry us too far. I ſhould not have done in an hour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll hear you patiently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>The Task you lay upon me is conſiderable; but I will not undertake to perform it with any regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity and exactneſs, nor will you expect it, ſpeaking of this in Converſation, and as an Amuſement. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I think there can be no <hi>Caſtles in the Air</hi> more agreeable than this. It were well if Thoughts of this nature were ſometime entertained: <hi>What good a Man would do, if he had Power.</hi> By this means all ill Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms might be diſcovered, examined, and in time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied. For it cannot but be the deſire of every well minded Man, to rectifie to the beſt of his power that which appears to him to be amiſs. There are many things which are evidently ſo; The Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of ſome is not altogether ſo conſpicuous to every one; Some are of the greateſt conſequence; And ſome tho' not ſo material, yet have their bad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96950:13"/>And ſome Practices are neglected, which in a high meaſure, and others which in a lower de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree would be conducive to Mens Happineſs, here and hereafter. I ſhall not treat of theſe Things, but hint ſome of them, as they ſhall preſent themſelves to my Thoughts.</p>
                     <p>If I was then an Adept, and were to negotiate with a Prince and Country, as you have put the caſe, I would firſt of all have theſe Matters taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Deliberation.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Touching Adepts. It ſhould be conſidered that Adepts, if there are ſuch Men, are the Servants of God, and dear to Him, ſeeing they are Men who ſeek the Kingdom and Glory of God in the firſt place; and denying worldly Luſts, live religiouſly and virtuouſly, and are zealous of good Works, and particularly of doing good, looking for the glorious coming of God our Saviour. Therefore it ſhould be in the firſt place regulated, and proviſion made that all Adepts, when known, ſhould be protected, and maintained in their full Liberty, as other Men would deſire to be, if they were Adepts: Otherwiſe, it were both the greateſt Injuſtice, and the higheſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption that Men can be guilty of; for thereby Men ſhould not only injure and oppreſs the Innocent, (whom God will avenge, for right Dear in the ſight of the Lord is the Death of his Saints, and of them God ſays, who toucheth them toucheth the Apple of my Eye;) but in perſecuting Adepts, they ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be found to fight againſt God, for Adepts ſeek only the Glory and Kingdom of God. Woe be therefore to the wicked Perſons, who are guilty of ſo great an Impiety, if they do not timely repent! May God ſuddenly change their Hearts, and make the Way plain before his Servants and Miniſters, that they be not always rejected, but may be at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; that Righteouſneſs and Equity may flouriſh
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96950:14"/>in the World! I would not have Adepts be only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to traffick of their Gold for their Occaſions, and the Relief of the Poor, but I would alſo (if it was thought good) have them to be admitted to the ſhare of Government that were offered, that is, if they approved of it. Was I a Sophi, I would not meddle with the Publick Adminiſtration of Affairs; and it is highly probable Adepts would not neither, if they might. But what were chiefly to be deſired for Adepts, is that their Perſons were declared ſacred, next to the Perſon of the Prince, and that they might have ſo much Power (by the Publick Acts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Prince and Nation,) as to live <hi>freely,</hi> and without danger, and to be abſolutely <hi>free</hi> to give their aſſiſtance, or to deny it, as the Acts of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they lived in, diſpleaſed or pleaſed them, and, in their Opinion, tended effectually to the Glory of God and the Good of Mankind. I would therefore have a ſtrong Houſe to be built, in faſhion like a Colledge, in the middle of the Metropolis, and this Colledge accommodated with neceſſary Furniture and Attendants. The Attendants ſhould be ſworn; and the Government ſhould publiſh a ſolemn Declaration, engaging themſelves, by the moſt ſacred Proteſtations, to guard and protect in full Liberty the Adepts that ſhould repair to the ſaid Houſe, admit them to a ſhare of Authority (that were limited) if they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it; and if they would not, to make, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that Colledge a ſure Refuge to them, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to have what Servants or Attendants they pleaſed, and to take of them their Gold at the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary rate at which that Metal is ſold, providing them whatſoever they would have at the Market or current Price, exacting nothing extraordinary from them for all this, being content with what Gratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they would voluntarily make to the Publick; in ſhort, leaving them their intire Liberty, and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96950:14"/>and protecting them againſt all danger. Such a Preparation being made for the Reception of the Adepts, a Declaration like that I have mentioned, but more particularized, ſolemn and full, would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly invite them, if there are any ſuch Men in the World. (Then would come to paſs, what one of them foretells of himſelf and his Brethren: <q>—I do not write theſe things, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> out of a vain Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but I ſee them in the Spirit. When we Adepts ſhall return from the four Corners of the Earth, nor ſhall we fear any Snares that are laid againſt our Lives, but we ſhall give thanks unto the Lord our God.—And now glorious things are declared of the City of God.—The New Jeruſalem ſhall abound with Gold in the Streets, and the Gates thereof ſhall be made of entire Stones, and moſt precious Ones; and the Tree of Life, in the midſt of Paradiſe, ſhall give Leaves for the healing of the Nations.—Theſe things will accompany our ſo long expected and ſuddenly approaching Redemption.</q> O Bleſſed the Governour and State to whom they ſhall come!) Now if there came never ſo many, I would aſſociate them to me if I were an Adept, and had Power; for there were no reaſon I ſhould have more Authority than they: Contrariwiſe, they being my Elders in Philoſophy, ſhould have the preference of Seniority, and I would undoubtedly yield it them, only all ſhould have equal Priviledges, and equal Votes in determining of publick Benefits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, Touching Religion. Suppoſing I had to do with Proteſtants, I would have the Proteſtant Principles exactly conſidered and followed, that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Comprehenſive Terms of Union being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed unto, there might be Love and Peace among thoſe that walk by the ſame Rule; there being no Edification, where there is no Charity, and where Partiality, Animoſity and Contention is preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Simplicity of the Goſpel; it being alſo a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96950:15"/>ſhame to hold Principles in the Theory, and viſibly to contradict them in the Practice; this, in fine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe of all the Confuſion among Proteſtants, and being ſuch a Scandal as infinitely prejudiceth thoſe from without againſt the Reformation, and even againſt Chriſtianity in general. The common Principles of Religion ſhould be chiefly inſiſted on, and all Men ſhould be carefully taught them, and obliged to live according to 'em. No body ſhould be forced in Matters that are controverted; for all Religion is taken away, if it be performed contrary to the inward Perſuaſion: Liberty of Conſcience ſhould therefore univerſally be allowed to all that are Religious, and ſollicitous to worſhip God after that manner which they ſincerely believe to be moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Will. But, on the other hand, no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhould be ſuffered to live irreligiouſly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World; for that is even contrary to the common Light of Nature, and right Reaſon. All, in every Pariſh, ſhould declare, before the Officers of the National Church, what Perſuaſion they are of, and what Sect they will adhere to. If any did not belong to any Sect that is known in the Country where he liveth, he ſhould be examined to ſee if he is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely of his Profeſſion, with knowledge of the cauſe, and if he can give an Account and Reaſon of his Faith; then he ſhould be inſtructed in the Principles of the Proteſtant Religion, and made to underſtand them, and to be able to judge of them, and ſhould be exhorted to Unity; in fine, if he perſiſted in his Superſtition, it ſhould be conſidered, Firſt, Whether no part of his Worſhip were contrary to the Duties of a peaceable Subject; for if it were ſo, he ſhould be kept under reſtraint, otherwiſe he ſhould enjoy his Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Secondly, it ſhould be conſidered whether he be a religious and ſincere Man, that abſtains from the publick Worſhip, thro' tenderneſs and ſcruples of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96950:15"/>Conſcience, and not out of Libertiniſm; for if a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine and an irreligious Perſon, he ſhould be fined and corrected, noted with Infamy, and declared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of any Truſt, 'till a known and laſting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; if a pious and conſcientious Man, he ſhould be tolerated, tho' never ſo erroneous in his Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Thoſe that adhered to ſome Sect, of which there were ſome Congregation within or near the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, ſhould be obliged to learn their Principles well, and particularly the common Principles of Religion, to be able to give a good account of them; they ſhould be obliged to fix upon ſome Congregation of which they ſhould be Members, to frequent conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the publick Worſhip in the ſaid Congregation; and the Officers of that Congregation, ſhould be bound to give an account of thoſe Perſons to the Pariſh-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the National Church, that if they gave not attendance to, or behaved not themſelves well in their Congregation, they might be accordingly puniſhed. Thoſe that are Members of the National Church, ſhould be obliged to frequent it conſtantly. No Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſhould be larger, than to be able to contain all the Pariſhioners in the Church with eaſe; and the Church ſhould lie the moſt convenient, in the middle of the Pariſh. There ſhould be publick Worſhip in every Church, conſtantly, four times a day, every day of the Year; and every Pariſhioner ſhould be preſent to the publick Worſhip twice a day conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, otherwiſe he ſhould, firſt, be ſubject to the Church-Cenſures, and ſhould be admoniſhed openly in the Church, and, ſinally, if he repented not, after warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſhould be ſined, by the Civil Power, as a ſcandalous and obnoxious Perſon. It were a ſhame for Chriſtians to plead Occupations, to excuſe them from worſhipping God publickly one half hour twice a day, or to offer any Plea, for not uſing a ſhort Prayer in their Families, particularly when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96950:16"/>God's Creatures, when Jews and Turks, when in their own Countries, would bluſh to ſhew ſo little Devotion. But it is, yet, a greater and more burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhame, that among Chriſtians there ſhould be millions of Men that are ignorant of the firſt Elements of Chriſtianity, and are not taught to give one Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they ſhould be of the Chriſtian Religion. I would therefore that Proteſtants ſhould be conſtantly Catechiſed, publickly, or privately, all the year round, 'till they were thirty years of Age, or knew their Religion well, and were able to give a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, not by Rote, but by Reaſon and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Cuſtom would make it eaſie to them. There ſhould be ſeveral ſorts of Catechiſms printed and uſed, not only for the youngeſt Children, but ſome alſo for more aged Perſons, where the Prooſs of Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, and the Truth of Chriſtianity were clearly taught. And they ſhould have Diſcourſes read to them in an exact order upon all the Duties of Religion, and all the parts of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, upon the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue, the 5th, 6th, and 7th Chapters of St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, &amp;c. Preachers generally preach up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on arbitrary Subjects, without Order or Regularity; ſo that a Preacher ſhall have lived ten years in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, without having explained to his Auditors one half of their Duties, commonly contenting himſelf to exhort them to Obedience, in general, in every Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; whereas they ſhould underſtand well every Command which they ought to obey, and ſhould have repreſented to them the ſeveral Conſiderations and Motives to Obedience neceſſary as to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. I would therefore that the Book of the whole Duty of Man, and the beſt Books that ſhould be printed from time to time upon all the Parts of Religion, ſhould be read in an exact Order, one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, in every Church, every Lord's Day in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96950:16"/>the Afternoon: And then, as for the morning Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, it might be left to the Pariſh-Miniſter to chuſe what Subject he would enlarge upon. There are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Points which are not, ordinarily, treated at all, as not being eaſie to be touched upon, or not very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be taken notice of, concerning which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs an infinite number of People want both to be informed and admoniſhed of their Duty; as the Duty of Reſignation, the Diſpoſition of being ready to ſuffer for Religion, and ſeveral Branches of Juſtice, Humility and Charity, that generally are not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the beginnings and leſſer Acts of Impurity, againſt which ſcarce general Warnings and Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ever given, as if Purity and Continence in the leaſt Acts contrary to Chaſtity were not neceſſary to qualify Men for Heaven; the heatheniſh Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of obſerving lucky or unlucky Seaſons and Days, of being awed by Omens, as the ſpilling of Salt, the croſſing of a Hare, the flight of ſome Birds, uſing Charms for Cures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I would have theſe Things to be taken notice of and rectified. It is certain, that thoſe that have the cure of Souls, do not give ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inſtructions and Exhortations to their People, nor ordinarily can well do it, becauſe they have too many committed to their Charge. A Miniſter ſhould not only know all his Pariſhioners by their Names and Sirnames, but ſhould be perſonally and intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted with them, ſhould be informed of all their Diſpoſitions and Inclinations, and ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſit them, as their Guide, when they are Sick, but chiefly and moſt frequently when they are in Health, to prepare them for a good Death and a happy Eternity. It is not enough to give ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Exhortations, in publick, in a formal Diſcourſe that cannot be comprehended by the three quarters of the Multitude: Familiar Dialogues and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in Meekneſs and with Gravity, are incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96950:17"/>more home; becauſe generals are applied to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one's Caſe, and every one's Difficulties are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. I would therefore that all Pariſh-Miniſters were accountable, to their Superintendants or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, whether they had a particular Conference, concerning Religion, of one hour at leaſt, every Month, with every one of their Pariſhioners without Exception. Theſe religious Conferences ſhould be in the room of the primitive Confeſſions in the ancient Church. There ſhould be no day without ſome of them. And every day, at a certain time, all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techumens in the Pariſh ſhould repair to the Church, to be inſtructed during two hours, and ſhould not only be askt their Catechiſm by Rote, but ſhould be taught to give ſome anſwer of themſelves upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Subject. There are few Miniſters that ſpend the quarter of their time in the diſcharge of their Duty: But I'd make no Agreement, as that you have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or Miniſters ſhould have all their time taken up in the Offices belonging to their Charge, and ſhould not paſs in the World for an unprofitable Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and a Company of uſeleſs Men. You'll ſay, Can Men live without Diverſion? They muſt find Diverſion in their Employment. Shall Miniſters preach to the Men of this World, that they muſt be aſſiduous as well as faithful in their Vocations, and ſhall they themſelves be careleſs in their high Calling, and do the Work of God negligently? They may have the Diverſion of ſometimes writing popular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, then reading excellent Authors, then viſiting their Pariſhioners and conferring with them, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing the Catechumens, afterwards they may take the Recreation of a Walk, of reading News and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting themſelves in their own Familiy, familiarly converſing with their Friends, and inſtructing their Servants, and their Children. But on pain of being ſuſpended and depoſed, they ſhould not be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96950:17"/>to ſpend their time in Gaming, or Fiſhing, Fowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hunting, or any Employment beſides that of watching to their Flock. The Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners depends, in a very great meaſure, on the good Example and aſſiduous Inſtructions of thoſe whoſe Office it is to teach the People; and if they loſe their Savour, wherewith ſhould the whole Lump be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned? It is therefore of the higheſt conſequence to inſiſt upon this, and indiſpenſably require effectual Proviſion to be made that Miniſters acquit themſelves exactly and fully of their Duty. All the Miniſters ſhould ſend every Year to their Dioceſan an account of the Texts they have preached upon, and a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, at the leaſt, of the bigneſs of a Sermon, upon ſome Theological Subject; and the Diſcourſes which the Biſhop ſhould judge fitteſt, ſhould be printed. A certain number of Pariſhes ſhould be aſſociated, thro'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Nation, to erect a Lecture, upon ſome week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, in the biggeſt Town within the Circuit, and all the Miniſters of the ſaid Pariſhes ſhould be obliged to meet there, that day, not only to be preſent at the Lecture-Sermon in the Morning, but alſo to confer together, during three hours at leaſt, in the Church, in the Afternoon, to propoſe Difficulties, to render an account of their Behaviour, and of the ſtate of their Flock to one another, and to perform Theological Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, quoting all the Texts of Scripture in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Languages, that they might be all obliged to continual ſtudy, and not permitted to leave off the reading of Theology as ſoon as they have ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, as many too ordinarily do. It is not one Miniſter in a hundred, that ever ſtudieth to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Bible, as he ſtudied a Claſſical Author, or that ſo much as ever reads it thro' with ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries and Annotations; tho' it be his Profeſſion to explain the Bible, and tho' it be granted on all hands by Proteſtants, that the Word of God explains
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96950:18"/>it ſelf, one place by another, that the pureſt Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy is to be drawn from thence, and that it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt neceſſary ſtudy. But to put a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity on all Miniſters to underſtand the Bible, they ſhould be obliged to explain two whole Chapters of it every Lord's-day Morning, and two other Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Afternoon, the one Chapter being always the firſt Leſſon of the Service, in the Old Teſtament, and the other, the ſecond Leſſon in the New: The Leſſon ſhould firſt be read altogether, and then brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly explained, one Verſe after another. Cuſtom would render this very eaſie. But if ſome could not perform it themſelves, there ſhould be ſuch Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all the Verſes of the Bible printed, and they ſhould be permitted to chuſe thoſe which they liked, and to read them, making what alterations they found neceſſary, if in any place they judged they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Text better than the Explicator in that occaſion. By this means no Miniſter could be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from explaining all the Word of God to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But you'll ſay, Muſt there be no Prayers, and how will a Miniſter be able to do all this, and then preach? I anſwer, Many Expedients may be found out for that. All Men may be taught to read well; there is ſcarce a Pariſh now but where there are ſome that can do it: They ſhould be obliged, by the Church Cenſures, to take Deacons Orders, and to ſerve the Church, <hi>gratis,</hi> in thoſe Things which they were capable of, and which ſhould be no hindrance to them from their Buſineſs, it requiring no extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Learning or Application, and they being in conſcience bound to be always preſent to the Divine Service; wherefore they might read in the Aſſembly moſt of the printed Books that were read, and the Common-Prayers. The Miniſters on whom Study, Writing, and Teaching were incumbent, ſhould be ſpared in all the Occaſions that others might ſupply
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96950:18"/>their room in; and as I ſaid, they ſhould have no greater number of Pariſhioners, than they could take a due care of; and therefore the extent of Pariſhes ſhould be limited. It will be objected, that then there muſt be a greater number of Miniſters, and conſequently a greater Proviſion made for them. I anſwer, There might be many ways found to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, without being burden'd thereby; but there would be no difficulty in that, if there were Adepts, and if they had Power. I ſhall only obſerve that I would have the fifth part of the Revenue of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters laid up every Year by the Publick, for the uſe of thoſe of their Widows and Children that might want it. I may now ſpeak ſomewhat of Churches, and the manner of uſing them. I would have Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries to be in every Church, to place all the Women there by themſelves, ſeparately from Men; and the Galleries ſhould be cloſed all over with Glaſs-win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows that ſhould be ſixed, from the Fore-front <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the Galleries to the Roof of the Church, to hinder the immodeſt and irreligious Cuſtom of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men gazing upon one another during Divine Service. No Body ſhould bow and cringe, and make ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and vain Poſtures to one another in Churches, under pain of Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures. No Carpets, nor other ſigns of Vanity and Reſpect of Perſons ſhould be ſuffered in the Church. For what do'ſt thou mean, O vain Perſon; do'ſt thou ſhame and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult upon them, that have not like thee, even in the immediate Preſence and under the Eyes of God? In particular, there ſhould be no burying, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no Grave-Stones, Inſcriptions, nor Eſcut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheons in Churches; and there ſhould be no manner of Pictures, or carved Work there. The Veſtibulum and Chancel of ever Church ſhould be extraordinary ſmall, for when they are otherwiſe there is a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity, and they render the Church dangerouſly cold
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96950:19"/>in Winter-time; whereas it ought to be made as commodious as poſſible, that the Pariſhioners may conveniently remain in it three or four hours in the Morning, and as much in the Afternoon every Lord's-day; for if People have Devotion, will Worſhip God, and be inſtructed as they ought to be, they can allot no leſs time: It is but riſing two hours ſooner; and what is this to riſing conſtantly in the night, or ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whole nights and days in God's Publick Service, as the Primitive Chriſtians thought not too much to do? Sometimes in the Time of Divine Service, while a Pſalm is ſung, ſome of the Officers of the Church ſhould obſerve, whether all the Pariſhioners were preſent. Expreſſions of the Pſalms, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Imprecations according to the ordinary Verſions, ſhould be tranſlated in the future Tenſe; and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Hymns ſhould be compoſed, in Imitation of thoſe of <hi>David.</hi> There ſhould be a Communion in every Church every firſt Lord's-day of the Month; in order to the re-union of ſcrupulous Perſons, it might be received ſtanding; but as ſoon as received, the Communicant ſhould kneel down by the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table, to make his thanks-giving Prayer to God, and then he ſhould retire; but that the Communicant's Devotion ſhould not be diſturbed, there ſhould be a Way to go from every Seat to the Communion Table, and another Way to return back, to avoid the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of meeting and juſtling one another. When there ſhould be publick and ſolemn Faſts, as <hi>Good-Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> &amp;c. if any one did eat publickly before the Even, he ſhould be put to death. And when days of Thanks-giving, at any time ſhould be ordained, it ſhould be Impriſonment for a Month, with a Fine at leaſt of Twenty Pounds, for any one to be drunk on that day. In ſhort, we ſhould be truly Religious, and ſhould not mock God, if we would have him to bleſs us. I ſhall conclude this large Head with an Order that has
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96950:19"/>a little relation to Religion, tho' it be not moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial: I would have the old heatheniſh names of Days and Months to be changed into ſome, that were more Chriſtian-like.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Touching Government. It ſhould be the eaſieſt that were poſſible, the ſafeſt and moſt glorious for the Governors, and the Governed. It ſhould be ſuch, that all might live in Concord and love, and without Jealouſie. I would not therefore accept of Arbitrary Power, if it were offered. The Law, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by the Judges and the Repreſentatives of the People, ſhould be the ſupream Rule. For let a Prince be never ſo juſt and good, yet if he will have no boundaries, and if his Will be the Law, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects will ever miſtruſt him, there will never be that mutual Affection, that Unanimity, and that Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Mind on which the common Tranquillity and Happineſs depends. It is then moſt advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to Princes, as well as to the Subjects, that the People have their ſhare of the Power, eſpecially in making of Laws, ordering the Subſidies, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them to the beſt uſes for the Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all this I would have to be made, by Law, the Rights and Priviledges of a venerable Senate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed partly of the Nobles of the Land, and partly of a certain number of the moſt Expert, the moſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, and the moſt Vertuous among the People, choſen and nominated by the People themſelves. And to this I would have further Power, and Privileges yet added; namely, that this venerable Senate not only ſhould meet when ever its majority thought beſt to meet; but, Secondly, That it ſhould have its ſhare alſo in nominating to Offices, and Places of Truſt, that there might be leſs occaſions, then, of Jealouſie; Thirdly, That the People ſhould ſwear Fidelity and Obedience to the Senators, as well as to the Prince and the Aſſociated Adepts; and, Fourthly, That as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96950:20"/>the Senators ſhould ſwear Fidelity to the Prince and the Adepts, the Prince and the Adepts ſhould alſo ſwear Fidelity to the Senators, and that if any one of theſe three Parties, the Prince, the Adepts, and and the Senate did fail or miſtake in any Point pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and comprehended in the ſaid Oaths, the Party thus failing on its part, ſhould be judged by the other two, accompanied and aſſiſted of the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trators and Umpires, that is, all the Judges of the Land, and of twenty of the generally reputed the beſt, the moſt juſt and moſt vertuous Men in the Nation, who ſhould be choſen by all the Parties and Judges jointly, and ſhould have a-like Votes with them: Thus Matters ſhould be quietly and peaceably adjuſted, when any Differences ſhould ariſe. I ſhould think theſe Regulations neceſſary, not only for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Aſſurance of the People, but alſo for the Advantage and Security of the Prince and the Adepts. For the Adepts ſharing, then, with the Prince, of the Power and Privileges which he before enjoyed alone, it would be preſumed that they would ſupply him with the Sums without Limitation, that he might have occaſion for; and for that Reaſon the People might grow Jealous both of the Prince and the Adepts, which would undoubtedly be of a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence, and poſſibly in time render the whole Nation miſerable: But all theſe Miſchieſs ſhould be prevented by the expedient I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Some, not regarding that all this is founded upon a Suppoſition, will perhaps ask; what King would thus part with his Privileges to a Company of Philoſophers, and to his People; would not that be unworty of a Prince; would it not be injurious to his Memory; and would it not make him the leſs great, for the preſent, and his Eſtate leſs glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? I anſwer then, This would be infallibly the way to render his State eaſie and agreeable; to cauſe him to be infinitely beloved and honoured of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96950:20"/>all People; to tranſmit his Name with admiration to Poeſtrity; and which is the beſt, to make him the Friend of God, to aſſure to him an everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to crown him with Felicity to everlaſting Ages. He ſhould for ever be called the Father of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the Angels ſhould extol his Praiſes in Heaven; they ſhould carry the bleſſed News to the holy Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants above; they ſhould name him the <hi>Foſter</hi>-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church, the Reſtorer of Liberty and Chriſtianity, the Lover of the Saints, the Protector of his Brethren, the Benefactor of Men. O bleſſed Prince; whom his Subjects, whom all Men, whom the Saints and Angels, whom God himſelf would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to praiſe and love, and combine to make him Happy! Thus for ever bleſſed, would ſuch a Prince be. Thoſe that preferred any Conſiderations before this, might enjoy their Choice; they ſhould not be envied by others. The Prince that ſhould offer a ſhare of his Power to the Adepts, would never repent it, tho' it be probable they would not accept it, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to have and enjoy their Liberty without danger, as was ſaid under the firſt Head. You won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der perhaps that I always call him Prince, they whom you mentioned being Kings. But 'tis not derogatory to a King, to call him Prince in ſpeaking of him. And I confeſs, I would rather chuſe to term him Prince or Emperor, if I were to negotiate as we have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, becauſe I ſhould not know whether Adepts would not then have the Name of King and the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Majeſty to be conſecrated to God: I would therefore in ſuch a Caſe have that to be referred to them, if it were ſo liked, and would not otherwiſe nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate. This illuſtrious Prince, the Adepts and Senate ſhould concur in encouraging and rewarding Vertue, and diſcountenancing and puniſhing Vice. Inſtead of other Military Orders, ſhould be inſtituted the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Holy Bible.</hi> The Arms of the Adepts, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96950:21"/>be affixed to their Colledge-Gate, ſhould be a Lamb crowned, placed over all, in the midſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Arms, if it were ſo agreed; the Coat ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by two Angels. The Senate ſhould have its Coat of Arms likewiſe. No Senator ſhould be capable of that Office, that were legally proved to be a ſwearer, an irreligious Perſon, or the like. The Senators that ſhould have made any Feaſts, or given any Bribes, to be elected, ſhould be expelled out of the Senate, ſeverely ſined, and impriſoned. It ſhould be made the higheſt Crime, for a Senator, and for a Judge, to take any Bribes; but they ſhould be well provided for, and Senators ſhould have a conſiderable yearly Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the State. No Senator ſhould ever be armed, but ſhould wear a Robe to diſtinguiſh him, and make him known: It ſhould be a capital Crime for Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to bring any Arms in the Senate-Houſe; but they ſhould have publick Guards, of their nominat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The conſtant ſtudy of the Government ſhould be to make their own People happy, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make their Neighbours ſo too, not by fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, but by giving them good Counſel; and they ſhould ſend vertuous and learned Men all the World over, to preach to the Poor and Ignorant (not Controverſies, but) the moſt indiſputable Points of Chriſtianity.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, Touching Subſidies, and the Proviſions for the Security of the Society. It were not juſt that a People ſhould do nothing for the Publick Security and Proſperity: Adepts would never concur with ſuch unreaſonable Deſires; neither would they make it ſo palpably evident to the World, that the Nation was ſupported with their Gold. They would not deny their Supplies, when they were neceſſary; but they would let the People provide for ordinary Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; therefore there ſhould be always a Tax im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, if it were but a Penny in the Pound, and an
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96950:21"/>equal Poll, according to every one's Ability, tho' it were never ſo little: And not only ſo, but to leave the World uncertain, whether the Aſſociated Adepts had the Art of making Gold, or were only wiſe Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians, who knew how to perſuade the rich People in the Nation to entruſt them with great Sums, to be employed for the beſt advantage of the Publick, they ſhould have an Office, before the Entrance of their Colledge, where ſome of their moſt truſty Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers ſhould be continually attending, to receive what well diſpoſed Perſons would voluntarily commit to their management for the Occaſions of the Government, whether in coined Mony, Ingots of Metal, Pearls, and Jewels, or Letters of Exchange; and this ſhould be called, the <hi>Free-gift-Office,</hi> or the like. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, they might have Officers, that ſhould Traffick in the <hi>Indies.</hi> As for the Security of the Society, that ſhould conſiſt (under God's Protection) in a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and well equipped Fleet, in a well diſciplin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Militia, and a few Land-Soldiers. The Names of the Militia-Men ſhould be Regiſtred in Publick Rolls, to oblige the ſame Men to ſerve conſtantly, after they had voluntarily enrolled themſelves. They ſhould conſtantly be exerciſed, one day every Week, in every Pariſh; ſhould have two Shillings every time, with a neceſſary Proviſion of Powder, and the Adepts ſhould bear all the Charge: But thoſe of them that ſhould be convicted to be habitual Swearers, Drunkards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be ſeverely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. The Armies, both upon Land and Sea, ſhould be Nurſeries of Piety and Vertue; every Soldier ſhould be obliged to have a well conditioned Bible and Prayer-Book, and ſhould conſtantly aſſiſt, every day, twice, to the Publick Devotion and reading of God's Word. Seamen in time of Peace, and Soldiers in Corps de Gard, and when they were not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally taken up with Military Duty, ſhould not be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96950:22"/>permitted to Game and Play, but ſhould be taught their Catechiſm, if they knew it not; ſhould hear Divine Service; and in fine, ſhould be obliged to read or Work. They might be taught alſo, Writing, Navigation, Mathematicks, and other Sciences uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them. They ſhould be moſt ordinarily occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied in Fencing and Shooting at a Mark. Sometime, they might be employed in mending the High-Ways, and in other Works for the Benefit of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
                     <p>Fifthly, Touching the Governours Duty of taking an equal Care of all the Subjects in general. The Govemours ſhould not only take care that thoſe of whom they receive large Supplies, and who have a great deal to give, ſhould fare well and ſubſiſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably; but if they would be the Fathers of their Country in general, and not the Fathers of the Rich only, they ſhould have the ſame Concernment for all the People. They ſhould therefore ſtudy ways and means that the Multitude might live, by their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and Induſtry, more generouſly and eaſily than they now do, being debaſed, by their ill Fortune, and their Spirits and their Vivacity almoſt depreſſed to the dulneſs, or changed into the ferocity of Brutes. Every Man, therefore, to be tolerably well, ſhould be enabled to get eighteen Pence a day, at leaſt, all the Year round, throughout the Nation; every Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a Shilling; and every Child, from ſeven Years to fifteen, three Pence, four Pence, ſix Pence. There ſhould be ſome peculiar Arts and Works, as the moſt neat and eaſie, which ſhould be, by Law, reſerved for Families that have had Eſtates, and are, without their fault, fallen to decay, for Children whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for Widows whoſe Husbands had Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments worth fifty or three ſcore Pounds a Year, or upwards, and are now become Poor, by the loſs of the Head of the afflicted and deſolate Family.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96950:22"/>Theſe Works ſhould have ſuch a Price ſet upon them by the Law, that every one might get two Shillings or half a Crown a day: And other Perſons, beſides thoſe mentioned in the Law, that ſhould take upon them to make thoſe Works contrary to the legal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions, ſhould be made Slaves, and employed in the hardeſt Drudgeries for the Publick: If any brought over the like Manufactures from Foreign Countries, and thoſe that partaked with them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhould be puniſhed in the ſame manner without remiſſion. By this means there would be ſome equality, (more at leaſt, than is ordinary in this wicked and unjuſt World,) every one being able to live comfortably, and conveniently according to his Condition. It will be objected, that if every Work-man may get at leaſt eighteen Pence a day, there will ſcarce enow be found that will do the hardeſt Works, or that will ever be Servants. I anſwer, Thoſe that do the hardeſt Works muſt have three Pence, four Pence, ſix Pence a day, allowed them by the Law, more than others, and then they muſt be obliged, by the Law and the Church-Cenſures, to take thoſe Wages, and to follow thoſe Employments: A Maſon muſt be obliged to bring up his eldeſt Son a Maſon, and if this dieth before he have a Son, his next Brother muſt learn and profeſs the Trade, or fine ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to provide another Apprentice in his room; and thus for all other Trades: In caſe of neceſſity, the Publick might order the Juſtices to preſs as they ſaw occaſion, and diſpoſe of the Children of Work-men and Trades-men within their Circuit, to what Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Profeſſions were moſt wanted: Beſides, many condemned Malefactors might be made Slaves, and their Legs being chained, obliged to work for the Publick. As for Servants: No ordinary Man's Children ſhould be permitted to marry before they were thirty or five and twenty Years old; nor
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96950:23"/>ſhould be allowed by the Law, to live in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe after they were fifteen Years old, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Child, in every Houſe, to ſerve his Parents, if they wanted it; nor ſhould any of them be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to work for themſelves, from fifteen to thirty Years, but ſhould be obliged during that time to be in Service. Thus a due Order, as to this caſe, might be eaſily preſerved. There is nothing that Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ought more to ſtudy, than to maintain among their People a juſt equality as much as poſſible. Without Juſtice there can be no Charity, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that excellent Vertue, no true Chriſtianity. How few Nations then are Chriſtian, tho' they be called by that ſacred Name! Moſt pretended Chriſtians ſeek to do God Service, in things far from thoſe he has commanded; and they paſs by Judgment and Mercy. They ſtrain at a Gnat, the vile Gnoſticks; they lay the ſtreſs on nice Speculations, doating about Queſtions, and Strifes of Words; they glory in that they judge they have hit on a more certain Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe Obſcurities than other Men, and they cry to the Humble and Vertuous, ſtand off, odicus Wretch, I am holier than thou. What! tho' the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel be ſwallowed? Tho' thou walloweſt in Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, or deſireſt ſo to do, and ſeeſt thy fellow-creature want the Comforts and Neceſſaries of Life, and thou ſay'ſt he ought to have no Juſtice? Tho' thou killeſt or ſtarveſt the Innocent, the Meek, the Juſt, the Pious, the conſcientious Perſon? Tho' thou hazardeſt to ſight againſt God, and raſhly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeſt his Kingdom? O <hi>Babylon, Babylon!</hi> How cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal and deceitful? How many live in the midſt of thee, and ſay they are the Citizens of <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> I leave them to God, and ſhall only add, That it might be limited how much Lands any Man could poſſeſs; that thoſe that had too large a ſhare, ſhould diſtribute part of them to ſome of their Family and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96950:23"/>Kindred, and ſhould ſell ſome part to the Adepts, for the uſe of the Publick.</p>
                     <p>Sixthly, Touching Law and Phiſick. All abuſes, in them ſhould be reformed. The Government ſhould give ſet Stipends to Lawyers and Phyſicians; Law and Phyſick ſhould coſt nothing to the People; and if Phyſicians and Lawyers were convicted of having taken any Gifts, they ſhould be puniſhed, as thoſe that take Bribery. A certain mumber of Phyſicians and Lawyers ſhould be maintained within a Circuit, and there ſhould be Superintendents in the Nation, to have Inſpection over them. The ſame Perſon ſhould practiſe Phyſick and Surgery, and the Medicines ſhould be prepared at the ſick Man's, or at the next charitable Houſe, thoſe of his own Family buying the Drugs themſelves at the Drugſters, or at Ware-houſes ſet up for that purpoſe by charitable Chriſtians among the Rich, or by the Adepts. Thus Phyſicians ſhould not be permitted to make a Myſtery of their Art, for none ſhould adminiſter any Phyſick, of which all the Ingredients were not declared, except it were, abſolutely, <hi>gratis.</hi> Therefore they ſhould teach their Art, to as many as would learn it, for the Relief of Mankind: They ſhould, themſelves, prepare the Medicines, together with ſome of the ſick Man's Friends, Neighbours or Servants, and a Servant or Apprentice of the Phyſician's, that ſhould aſſiſt them. All Law ſhould be expreſſed in a vulgar Language, and in vulgar and intelligible Terms. The Subjects ſhould not be obliged to go far, nor to be at any Charges for Juſtice. Every Man, the wronged Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's next Neighbours, or any dwelling in the ſame Street with the Plaintiff, ſhould be obliged to do the Office of Bailifs, and upon refuſal or neglect, ſhould be conſiderably ſined. Lawyers that ſhould give a falſe Advice, ſhould be anſwerable for it. Moſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſhould decide in moſt Caſes; and at a certain
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96950:24"/>diſtance of ſome Miles, there ſhould be a Judge Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident. A Judge that ſhould have given an apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and viſibly wrong Judgment, or that ſhould have denied Juſtice, ſhould be ſeverely puniſhed; and it ſhould be eaſie, and of no charge to obtain a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt him, and redreſs from the wrong ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained by his unjuſtice. On the other hand, the Judge ſhould ſeverely puniſh the Party that ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before him in a viſibly and palpably wrong Caſe, when it were credible he ſaw what was right, and maliciouſly and contentiouſly refuſed to do it: This Enormity ſhould be puniſhed by Fine, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and corporal Puniſhment; otherwiſe there would be no end of contentious Suits, and a Judge could never reſt. No Perſon having Right of his ſide, ſhould ever be a loſer, or a ſufferer in the leaſt; whereas now an innocent Perſon being falſly accuſed, or unjuſtly brought before the Judges, tho' after great difficulty his Innocence at laſt, thro' God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, appears, he is yet half undone in his Eſtate, and his Accuſers, who appear to all the World to be perjured Villains and Infidels, are let go unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they ſhall not be made Examples nor be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from doing the like miſchief again, without he purſue them on freſh ſcore, and make an end of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ining himſelf. Theſe ways will inevitably draw God's Wrath upon a Nation, and will undoubtedly be puniſhed with everlaſting Curſe, without timely amendment. Thrice bleſſed are the People, whoſe God is the Lord, and who actually obſerve his Laws!</p>
                     <p>Seventhly, Touching Puniſhments. There ſhould be but few Criminals, condemned to die; Moſt of them that are ordinarily puniſhed with Death, ſhould be ſentenced to be the Publick's Slaves for their life; their Eſtates being conſiſcated for the uſes of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thoſe that had ſtolen any Goods from any
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96950:24"/>Man, ſhould work for him in Priſon, 'till they had reſtored two-fold the value of that which they had taken. Priſoners that were impriſoned for wicked Actions, ſhould have their Legs chained, and ſhould be obliged to hard work. None ſhould be idle, and, much leſs, ſuffered to be intemperate in Priſons. The Priſons ſhould be low Buildings, long and narrow, and full of Grates, that every one might ſee the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners work. There ſhould be Priſons for Women, diſtinct and ſeparate from thoſe for Men. The Keepers or Goalers, that ſhould be convicted to be Swearers, Drunkards, Extortioners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be made Slaves. Priſons ſhould not be the Debauchers of the miſerable, but rather Schools of Repentance and Vertue. All Strumpets that were caſt into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhould not go out from thence 'till they had learned a Trade, and had got the habit of working and living honeſtly. All Priſoners ſhould be obliged to aſſiſt at Divine Service conſtantly four times eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day; and the ignorant ſhould be catechiſed, and made to learn perfectly their Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>Eighthly, Touching Learning and Education. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that from the Education and Learning of young Perſons and Children, depends in a high meaſure not only the happineſs of having good and vertuous Citizens and Subjects, (which is the greateſt Felicity that Chriſtian Governours can enjoy upon Earth.) but alſo the happineſs of the governed themſelves, in this Life and the next; I would have therefore the beſt Books concerning Education to be ſometime read in Churches: And I would have ſuch Regulations made, that Inſpection ſhould be had over Parents and Maſters, to ſee whether they diſcharged themſelves well of their Duties towards their Children, Scholars and Servants in that particular. For Maſters are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitably bound to take care of the Chriſtian Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their Servants, as well as School-Maſters
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96950:25"/>are to anſwer for that of their Scholars, and Parents for that of their Sons and Daughters. Maſters ſhould therefore cauſe their Servants to read ſome Portion of the Bible every day, and if they had further time to ſpare them from their Buſineſs, ſhould oblige them to write, and learn ſomething uſeful by heart, but ſhould by no means ſuffer them to be idle; Idleneſs being the Mother of Corruption and Debauchery. Maſters that ſhould be convicted of neglect herein, ſhould be fined, diſgraced and declared uncapable of any truſt, not diſcharging themſelves of their Duty in their own Families, and thereby ſhewing that they have no Conſcience, that they do not fear God and have no Chriſtian Love or Concernment for their Fellow-Chriſtians, or Fellow-Creatures. But if it be the Duty of Maſters, to habituate their Servants to live vertuouſly and religiouſly; it is much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon Parents, to train up their Children in the Way they ſhould go. They ſhould, therefore, in the Firſt place, teach them the Principles of Piety; Secondly, Not uſe them to any Pride and Vanity, Delicacy or Eſſeminacy, but bring them up in the greateſt Plainneſs, to make them, by uſe, hardy, and manly, moderate, and inclined to look upon their Inferiours as Brethren, and upon all Men as equals in the main; Thirdly, Cauſe them to learn what it is neceſſary Perſons of their Condition ſhould know, and eſpecially accuſtom them never to be idle, but to love to be always employed in ſomething that may be uſeful to themſelves, and to the Society. The Clark, in every Pariſh, or ſome other Perſon, that ſhould be paid by the Adepts, ſhould teach all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to read, write, and caſt up Accompts, without coſting any thing to the Parents. Above all, Maſters ſhould be charged to take care, chiefly, that their Scholars ſhould not contract vicious Habits, as of Prophaneneſs, Lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ſhould ſet private
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96950:25"/>Obſervators over them, to watch to all their Actions; and for every Immorality, they ſhould be puniſhed more than for any other Fault: Theſe Rules ſhould be obſerved in all Schools, great and ſmall. Latin and Greek Schools ſhould be diſpoſed into as many Rooms and Apartments as Forms or Claſſes. Every Claſſis ſhould have a particular Maſter, as well as a particular Room, to avoid confuſion: And the School ſhould have a Place in the Church, appropriated for the Scholars to ſit in, in the view of their Maſters. All Forms ſhould be examined twice a Year, not by Perſons choſen by the School-Maſters themſelves, as is ordinary, but by the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, who ſhould take of them an Oath of examining impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially. If the Examiners found the Maſters to have been negligent in their Office, or that the Scholars had not learned the things that are to be taught in every Form, the ſaid Maſters ſhould be turned out. At every Examination, there ſhould be <hi>Praemia,</hi> of ſome value, appointed for thoſe that excelled in the knowledge of Religion, and Human Learning, to encourage and excite Scholars. For the ſame reaſon, in every Claſſis, there ſhould be two Emperors, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, a ſet number of Senators, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Places ſhould be diſtributed according to every one's merit, as it is practiſed by the beſt Maſters of Education. Beſides Languages, ſome other things ſhould be taught in Schools, to Children; as Chronology, Geography, Arithmetick, the beginnings of Rhetorick, and of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Hiſtory, in the vulgar Tongue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for they ſhould read, in Schools, Books written in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Tongue, as well as in Latin, Greek and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew. In the upper Forms, they ſhould be uſed to make Speeches or Declamations, in their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Language, againſt all Vices, one after another, (in order) and in the praiſe of every Vertue, and they ſhould recite them every firſt <hi>Monday</hi> of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96950:26"/>Month, all Strangers, that would, being admitted to hear 'em, the beſt of thoſe Speeches in the Year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be printed, and to win a <hi>Praemium;</hi> and at every Remove to the Univerſity, the beſt Scholars, without partiality, ſhould have ſome Penſion allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them by the Adepts, the Examiners being upon their Oath. No Scholar, that could not live at his own charge, ſhould be ſent to the Univerſity, if he were not extraordinarily learned, in all the things to be learned at School. They ſhould not be admitted at the Univerſities, without a long and ſtrict Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, in every particular. There ſhould be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Examiners, maintained for that purpoſe by the Adepts. Such ſtrict and rigorous Regulations ſhould be made, that none but the beſt Scholars ſhould have the Preferments of the Univerſities. All thoſe that ſhould have ſome Preferment, ſhould print ſomething every Year, more or leſs, upon ſome uſeful Subject. The Scholars for the firſt ſeven Years, ſhould be publickly examined at every Year's end; and thoſe that ſhould not be found to be proficient enough in that Year's learning, ſhould be degraded and put back one Year, half a Year, or 'till they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed the loſt Time; and they ſhould be puniſhed with the Impoſition of numerous Exerciſes. The firſt Year, beſides the bottom of Rhetorick, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Logick, they ſhould chiefly read all the beſt Latin and Greek Authors, and modern Hiſtory, and they ſhould make Exerciſes in the vulgar Tongue, as well as in Latin, that their Stile might be corrected, and that they might be taught to expreſs themſelves ſimply and naturally. They ſhould alſo be uſed every day to learn ſomething by heart, and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to recite Diſcourſes, in Publick, this, and the ſix following Years. The ſecond Year they ſhould go through Logick and Ethicks, ſtill reading the beſt Latin and Greek Authors, thorow, with their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96950:26"/>and the Bible in Hebrew. The third Year, they ſhould read Aſtronomy, Philoſophy, Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and, ſtill, Latin and Greek Authors. The fourth Year, they ſhould ſtudy ſome Body of Divinity, Law and Phyſick, and read the Bible with Commentators; then they ſhould take their firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, if the Examiners, upon their Oath, found them to be learned in all things which they were to be taught, by the Orders and Conſtitutions of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. The three following Years conſtantly, they ſhould have regularly red unto them Divinity, Law, and Phyſick, according to their Deſigns, in the beſt Method and Order. Then if they were found by the Examiners to be actually good Proficients, they ſhould take their ſecond degree; for the firſt ſhould not entitle any to go into Orders, or to practiſe Phyſick or Law, but the ſecond ſhould be a ſufficient Title, to be qualified for preſent Preferment, and therefore the Examiners ſhould be at leaſt as exact and ſtrict in this laſt Examination as in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and if they admitted any Perſon unworthy, themſelves ſhould loſe their Places. In order to a Maintenance of the Scholars, that could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe live ſo long in the Univerſity, there ſhould be ſome Proviſion made, according to their Degrees, Needs and Merits. Tuitions and Lectures ſhould coſt nothing to the Scholars. Beſides the publick Lectures and Exerciſes, there ſhould be particular Exerciſes and Lectures, conſtantly, all the Year, in every Colledge; and the Profeſſors ſhould be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Adepts. A cheaper way of living than is in uſe with us, ſhould be provided for Scholars at the Univerſities: They ſhould not have their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals from a Cook and a Butler, who making ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the ignorance and careleſneſs of Scholars, get an Eſtate with them in a few Years. This is to lock up the Key of Knowledge, by making Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96950:27"/>chargeable, and thereby hindring many from ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying who perhaps are moſt fit for it. The Board ſhould be fixed at a certain Rate: Ten Pounds a Year for ſome, twelve Pounds for others, fifteen Pounds for Bachelors, twenty Pounds for Fellows. There ſhould be ſeven Profeſſors to every Colledge: One to read always to the firſt Year, another to the ſecond Year, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Scholars ſhould be at leaſt two hours in the Morning, and two hours in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon with the Profeſſors, and two hours after Supper for religious Exerciſes, when ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly expounded ſome Chapters of the Greek Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, both by the Profeſſors, and the Scholars, <hi>Grotius de veritate Religionis Chriſtianae,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Practical Catechiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Profeſſors ſhould bring up Students of Divinity in the beſt Method of making Sermons, ſhould give them Texts to explain, and ſhould always criticiſe and correct their Diſcourſes; and they ſhould teach them to confer with all ſorts of Pariſhioners that may fall under their care, as the Superſtitious, thoſe that are Irreligious, and follow a bad courſe of Life, the Diſſenters, thoſe that are troubled in Mind, the afflicted, the ſick, and the like that require the Viſits and Counſels of Miniſters; that they might be ready for ſuch Occaſions. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſhould be of no charge at all to the Scholars, but, inſtead of that, the Scholars ſhould qualifie themſelves well for their Degrees, and truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them by their univerſal Learning. Scholars of different Colledges ſhould take their Degrees in different Months, thoſe only of one Colledge, or at moſt of two being examined at the ſame time; and they ſhould be examined publickly, during ſeven days, in their vulgar Tongue ſome days, and ſome other days in Latin, that they might be obliged to know how to expreſs themſelves well in both Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages. Every Maſter of Arts, (that could not live of his own Eſtate, and that were actually very skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96950:27"/>in all the parts of Learning,) as ſoon as he had taken that Degree, ſhould be allowed a good Penſion by the Adepts 'till he were diſpoſed of to ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, where he ſhould conſtantly exerciſe his Calling. In the Univerſities, as well as in inferior Schools, Scholars of all Years and of all Colledges ſhould have publick Places to ſit in, in their Church, according to their Colledges, Years and Seniority; and there ſhould be Obſervators, of every Colledge, to mark who came in time, or who were abſent. The Puniſhments in all Caſes, ſhould be the Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of large Exerciſes; and if thoſe were not duly performed, then ſhould follow publick Admonition; and, after a certain number of Admonitions, Expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: But Profeſſors ſhould never take Mony of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, who often, perhaps, care not what they coſt their Parents, or what becomes of their Mony. All the Sermons preached before the Univerſities, ſhould be printed at the publick charge. Neceſſary Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be allowed; but Idleneſs and Liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, going out of the Colledge at undue hours, or at any time without Permiſſion, Drunkenneſs, Fighting, Swearing ſhould be moſt ſeverely puniſh'd, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely hindred. Places, in fine, for the bringing up of Perſons of Quality, as our Inns of Court, Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be, likewiſe, ſo regulated, and inſpected, that good Hours, Temperance, and all the Duties of Piety ſhould be exactly obſerved by all; that thoſe Societies that were intended for the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Education of young Perſons, ſhould not be the Nurſeries of Wickedneſs, and the Schools of Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery and Irreligion.</p>
                     <p>Ninthly, Touching the way and manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for the Poor. That ſhould not be by allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the liberty of idly ſpending their Time in begging, but in providing them ſome Work, and obliging all that are in health and ſtrength, to labour
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96950:28"/>for their livelihood; but ſetling a competent Relief for the poor old Men and Children, the Widows and the Sick, the Lame and the Blind. As for Beggars, it is altogether unjuſt and unchriſtian to ſuffer any. For if they be able to work, but unwilling, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to let the Society be burdened by them, who far from being Objects of Charity, deſerve ſevere Puniſhment, and want it to be made to do their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; if they are able and willing to labour for their living, but have not been brought up in any Calling, or find no Employment, it is moſt juſt for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to provide them with, and put them in a way to live honeſtly, and not let them continue in Want and Idleneſs; if they can do but little, let them but be made to do that little which they are able; thoſe that have but one Leg, or one Arm, and old Men, and even thoſe that are blind, may do ſome eaſie things, and there is no reaſon they ſhould not do what they can; but thoſe that are diſabled to work, and thoſe that are ſick, it were moſt unchriſtian and barbarous not to maintain them, as we would our ſelves think it juſt to be comforted and maintained, if we were in their caſe. It is then, viſibly, horridly ſhameful to have Beggars in a Common-wealth. It is a ſign that there is little Charity and Chriſtianity, little Prudence and Order, or a great deal of Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and abſolute unability to make thoſe Proviſions that are neceſſary. This doth not mean that I would have Beggars to be hindred from asking Alms, as long as there is no ſufficient Proviſion made for them. That were the greateſt cruelty; it were to keep them, to torment 'em, by ſtarving them by degrees, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of relieving them. It is mocking God and Men, to ſay we take care of our Poor, when we allow ſix Pence, a Shilling or two Shillings, a Week, to them who have nothing elſe to depend on. Is that our Charity? Our loving other Men as our ſelves?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96950:28"/>Our doing to them, what we would they ſhould do to us, if we were in the like caſe? In good truth, ſhould we think that ſufficient, for all the Occaſions of Life? Why, then, do we not do juſtly? We are uſed to be unjuſt and partial in moſt things; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no wonder it is ſo here: We think nothing too good for us, and any thing good enough for others. A Merchant, a Nobleman, a rich Cardinal, think abundance of things neceſſary to their well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without which they would account Life a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect miſery. But a poor, honeſt Artizan, that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hard perpetually for the Society, they think, is well provided for, if he can get ſix Pence a day for his maintenance, and that of a Wife and ſeveral Children. What ſhould be done, will ye ſay? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That ſomething of Chriſtianity may appear, or ſomething like Charity, ſuch Conſtitutions ſhould be made, that thoſe whoſe living depends upon their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, might live agreeably and comfortably, as well as they that poſſeſs the Lands, and keep the Purſe. Which would effectually be, if what I have intimat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, under the fifth Head, were eſtabliſhed; if all ordinary Trades, that were uſeful and neceſſary, were encouraged by the Law, by alloting them good Wages; if the eaſieſt and neateſt Works were extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily paid, and reſerved for poor Perſons of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd quality, but fallen to decay; and if a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and ſufficient Proviſion were made for all the Poor. Then every Body ſhould be happy. The Rich, and thoſe that have Eſtates ſhould have the preference, and ſhould be moſt happy; and yet thoſe that have no Eſtates ſhould have no reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of their Lot. Fathers and Mothers would ſee all their Children in a way to live, without danger of miſery. None ſhould be miſerable, but the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Laws, and the diſturbers of this bleſſed Harmony. Then ſhould Righteouſneſs and Peace
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96950:29"/>kiſs each other, and Truth and Equity flouriſh upon Earth. The Rich ſhould not only enjoy the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their preſent Riches, but the ſatisfaction and tranquillity ariſing from the Conſideration of having done their Duty, and the comfort of ſeeing all Men, their Fellow-Creatures, and Fellow-Chriſtians, well provided for; they would be in no fear, that any of theirs ſhould ever want Neceſſaries, if, thro' any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune they came to loſe their Eſtates, being ſure of an ample Proviſion made for their living. The Trades-men and Artificers would have perpetual cauſe to love and praiſe the Rich, who gave them plenty, and rendred their life comfortable. Thoſe that were diſabled to work, being furniſhed with all the Things neceſſary for them, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>owed twelve Pence a day, or whatſoever were ſuitable to their former Condition, their Deſerts, and their preſent Neceſſities; the whole Society would partake of the temporal Felicity, <hi>promiſed</hi> to the practice of <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and the Obſervation of the Precepts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, the meaneſt and pooreſt Perſons being well. Bleſſed Times! Thrice bleſſed State, truly agreeable to the Deſign of Chriſtianity! Some will object, that our Saviour ſaith, That his Kingdom was not to be of this World, and that there ſhould be always poor People. I anſwer, We ſhall have always Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom we muſt relieve and take care of; but it doth not follow that we ought not to do it plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in a Chriſtian-manner, and according to Chriſtian-charity: And tho' our Saviour deſign'd not to Reign and Triumph perſonally upon Earth, with the Pomp and outward Glory of the Kings of this World, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declared ſo much to them, that they might be ſatisfied, there was no reaſon for them to be jealous of him; yet his meaning was not, that he would not have Men be ruled by his Laws, the Laws of right Reaſon and Wiſdom; indeed he would force no
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96950:29"/>Body, but by the Motives of Religion; and theſe are the Meaſures that true Philoſophers take. God's Servants repreſent the Duties of Religion to all Men; they do not conſtrain them to obſerve 'em, but if they will not obſerve 'em, they'll have nothing to do with them. But you will ſay, How can a ſufficient Proviſion be made for the Poor, except Adepts actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally do it? I anſwer, Something might be done to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the matter, according to Mens preſent Ability. Rich Men ſhould not think it below them, to be Overſeers for the Poor, and ſhould not truſt the Poor's Mony to mean Rogues, who make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Sacriledge. A Law might be enacted, to hinder all Pariſh-Meetings from being at all expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; it being a ſhame, that the Officers ſhould feaſt at the Poor's charge, moſt of whom in the mean time are ready to ſtarve. Means ſhould be thought of, to render it abſolutely impoſſible for Officers to do any wrong; the Boxes and Cheſts, in which they did take the Collections, and receive the Pariſhioners Charity, ſhould be of Iron, and carefully locked, like thoſe that are uſually carried about for Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and they ſhould be obliged to give their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts very frequently: Thoſe that ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of Sacriledge, ſhould be moſt exemplarily pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Then every one would have greater encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to part with his Mony, knowing it ſhould be actually put to the uſe to which he intended it. Dying Perſons might be perſuaded to leave Legacies to Hoſpitals and Alms-Houſes, and ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to it, ſeeing that Charity covereth a multitude of Sins, and that good Works of this kind may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be highly available, tho' there be no Purgatory after this life. In fine, if ſome Shillings in the Pound have been given ſeveral Years ſucceſſively to make War, it would not be impoſſible, after ſome time of Proſperity, to give, for one Year, one Shilling in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96950:30"/>the Pound for the Relief of Chriſt's Members. God, no doubt, expects that Men ſhould do for him what they are able; otherwiſe, he will do nothing for them. All the Laws therefore that may be made by rich Chriſtians in favour of the poor, he will one day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire from them. There are many things ſtill, which there would be great reaſon I ſhould inſiſt upon; but it being high time to draw to a concluſion, I ſhall croud together the Summaries of what might remain further to be enlarged, this ſhort Repreſentation being but the Chaos of the <hi>Sophick Conſtitution,</hi> or of God's Kingdom among Men. Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Tenthly, Touching Order and Policy in Cities, Buildings, and Commerce; Touching the improving the State and Riches of the Society, preventing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Expences and Vanities, and reforming all bad Cuſtoms as much as poſſible. If the Adepts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived large Preſents in the <hi>Free-gift-Office,</hi> mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fourth Head, I would have half the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Carpenters in the Land liſted, under condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good Wages, to the Service of the Publick, and mixed with the reſt of the Soldiers, to whom they ſhould teach their Trades. They ſhould exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in the Diſcipline of War one day of the Week, for the Grandeur and Security of the Nation. The other five work-days ſhould be ſpent in building Churches and Hoſpitals, making Fortifications on the Frontiers, paving all the High-Ways as they were paved here by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and repairing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building Towns and Cities. No Man ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to build a Houſe, except the Ground were his own, or except he purchaſed it, that he might have the greater encouragement to make the Houſe firm and ſtrong, ſeeing it ſhould remain to his Family af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him; whereas now Houſes are built too ſlightly. I would have Cities and Towns built ſquare, all the Streets ſtraight, broad, and equal; ſo that there
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96950:30"/>ſhould be no Lanes nor Allies, but the Streets ſhould be alike; all the Houſes ſhould have Piazza's as you ſee at <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> and under thoſe Piazza's ſhould be ſuffered no Sedans or Chairs to be carried, no Porters to go with their Burdens, no Lackies nor Children to play to diſturb and hinder the By-goers, nor ſmall Retailers there to expoſe their Wares, and ſtop the Paſſage, or ſpoil the Simmetry and Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of the Place; wherefore they ſhould be cloſe by the Pillars: Next the Piazza's, in the Street ſhould be reſerved a Walk for the Porters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Walk ſhould be paved with broad Stones, and fenced with Poſts, at an equal diſtance, againſt Horſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The middle of the Street ſhould be for Horſe-men, Carts, and Coaches: The Streets ſhould be paved with choice, ſmooth and even Stones, and every Houſe ſhould be obliged to cleanſe every day that part of the Street before it to the Kennel, under ſome Penalty: Croſs-way, in the middle, and end of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Street, or about the diſtance of every hundred Yards, ſhould be built from the Piazza's of one ſide of the Street, to the Piazza's of the other ſide, a kind of ſmall Bridge, high enough for Coaches to go under; it ſhould be broad, as the breadth of the Piazza's; it ſhould have fair and large Steps to go up, like the ſmall Bridges over the Channel by <hi>Fleet-ſtreet;</hi> and it ſhould be for the conveniency of thoſe that go a Foot, to croſs the Street, without being hindred or beſpattered by Coaches, and Carts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There ſhould be ſome By-ſtreets wholly ſet apart for Coach-houſes and Stables, none of which ſhould be ſuffered to be built in the other Streets. If the ſquare Form cauſed ſome intervals between Towns, built by a River-ſide, and the River, thoſe Plats of Ground ſhould be made beautiful Walks for the Publick; and if the River ran thro' part of the Town, the Houſes and Buildings, on both ſides the River, ſhould be all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96950:31"/>along of the ſame height, and equally magnificent. The Shops ſhould not be deep, but long, built length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way parallel to the Street, that they might be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, notwithſtanding the Piazza's. All Houſes ſhould have a Garden of an equal bigneſs, belonging to them; that the Air of Towns and Cities ſhould not be choaked, as it is ordinarily. Every one ſhould not have the liberty to live in the Metropolis that would; but that Priviledge ſhould be adminiſtred according to the Governor's Direction: All unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Perſons ſhould be obliged to remove to ſome other place. Brew-houſes, Glaſs-houſes, Pot-houſes, Candle-makers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be placed at two Miles diſtance, at leaſt, from Cities and Towns, by the River-ſide. Wood ſhould be burnt every where, ſome part of the Year. No Corps ſhould be buried nearer than half a Mile of every Town. There ſhould be common Shores, which every Houſe ſhould be obliged to make uſe of, to carry off all the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundicities of the Publick. In moſt Streets there ſhould be publick Houſes of Office, which ſhould be kept clean, thoſe that foul'd them being fined; thoſe ſhould be fined alſo, that ſhould make water in the Streets; that undecency not being to be ſuffered: A common Sentinel ſhould be ſet to ſtand before thoſe Houſes, and ſhould be reſponſible of keeping them neat. No Perſons extraordinary frightful and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, ſhould be ſuffered to go in the Streets, ſuch Objects ſtriking with horror the Beholders, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangerous to Women big with Child: If thoſe miſerable Perſons were not able to maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by reaſon of their Confinement, they ſhould be taken into ſome Hoſpital, built for that purpoſe. Theſe and the like Regulations ſhould be made, if I had Power, as you have ſuppoſed; and it may ſeem indeed ſtrange that moſt of them have not been made by moſt Nations of themſelves, before now. It will
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96950:31"/>be asked, which way could a ſufficient Fund be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, for ſo much Expence, as the moſt part of this would require? I anſwer, There are ſeveral ways, to improve the Riches of the Society, ſufficiently for this: Firſt, By granting publick Subſidies and Taxes to that end: Secondly, By the Rich, that were well diſpoſed, their ſending, freely, Preſents, according to their Abilities, to the Government, for thoſe and the like uſes: Thirdly, By dying Men leaving Legacies for the ſame purpoſe: Fourthly, By improving Lands to the beſt advantage: Fifthly, By obliging all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to exerciſe ſome Calling, or Employment uſeful to the Society: Sixthly, By hindering all Frauds and Unjuſtices in Commerce: And Laſtly, By prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all unneceſſary Expences and Vanities; and then, evil Cuſtoms being reformed as much as poſſible, God would not fail, on his part, to pour down his Bleſſings on a Nation ſo Piouſly and Chriſtianly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. As for improving Lands, it is certain that it might be done to a greater advantage for the Publick than it is, if Parks and Commons, and all unculti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated Grounds were cultivated and husbanded: And, every Body being obliged to concur, to the beſt of his power, to further the advantage of the Publick, and Laws being made againſt thoſe, who, following no Occupation or Employment to that end, were idle and unprofitable Members; Men would be incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably richer than they are, and able to do infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more good, and the ſame Country where the greateſt number is miſerable, would maintain plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully double the Inhabitants. Perſons that are rich, and have no near Relations, ſhould be exhorted to ſettle, before they died, their Parks and uncultivat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lands upon the Publick. Houſes might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receive all the Children that Particulars would ſend, which ſhould be employed all their life in the Publick's Service. The Unjuſtices and ill
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:96950:32"/>ways ordinarily practiſed in Trading, to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of the Society, ſhould be abſolutely hindred by wholſom Laws, and Cheating, Swearing, and even unreaſonable overrating in Selling ſhould be puniſhed, remembring that light Gains, in Commerce, make a heavy Purſe. Thus all fit Means ſhould be uſed to render every Man Rich, and make him live plentifully and comfortably. All Children ſhould be brought up ſo as to be ſtrong and hardy, and to be content with what is ſufficient, and is moſt fit to make them vigorous in Body and Mind; for by that means, they ſhall be Richer, with fifty Pounds a Year, than they would be with Two Hundred, being brought up Delicately and Effeminately, thereby making many ſuperfluous Things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their Happineſs; wherefore Parents cannot do worſe for their Children, nor do any thing more Unchriſtian, than to give them an effeminate Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, becauſe in making many ſuperfluous Things neceſſary to them, by Cuſtom, they oblige them to make their Portion too big, and conſequently that of others too little; they uſe them to deſpiſe, and tread under other Men, and to think highly of themſelves, and imagine that ſo they fare well themſelves, it is no matter for others; and then they reduce them to the neceſſity, in caſe their Eſtates thro' any accident fail them, either to be miſerable in the want of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinduced Neceſſaries, or to Damn their Souls to obtain thoſe Things by any Means. But if it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that Children be uſed to Temperance and Simplicity, and to a buſy and laborious Life; there is no leſs neceſſity, that Men always continue in the ſame Habit of Living. For Moderation, Induſtry, and Charity are always neceſſary, in order to preſent and future Happineſs. Men ſhould then, in ſome Meaſure, bear one another's Burdens; concur, in their ſeveral Stations, to do the affairs of the Society, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96950:32"/>and diligently, according to their ſeveral Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities; and deny themſelves thoſe Things which would be prejudicial to the Felicity of the whole Body. Therefore all unneceſſary Trades ſhould be aboliſhed, and unneceſſary Expenſes ſpared, to be applied to better Purpoſes. All Houſe Furniture ſhould be plain. There ſhould be no ſuch thing as Fringe, Lace, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidery, nor the like; or, elſe, thoſe that would have them, ſhould be fined the fourth part of their Revenues. All Playing for Mony, by which ſo much Time is loſt, and ſo many Families are ruined, ſhould be forbidden under ſevere Penalties, and the Mony, proved to have been played, ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſcated for the uſe of the Publick. Men ſhould be often exhorted againſt Delicacies, and exceſs in Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drinking; for if too much be allotted for this, there will be too little left for Charity; beſides that it is a Shame to make a God of one's Belly, like Brute-Beaſts, which know of no other Pleaſures than thoſe of Senſuality. To aboliſh the uſe of Tobacco, Snuſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thoſe that were not already uſed to them ſhould be forbidden them, under the Penalty of large Fines. Men ſhould alſo be forbidden, under the like Penalties, to make ſumptuous Feaſts, or to uſe Treats in Viſits; for by that means, Gluttony and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs are countenanced and brought into Faſhion, and while ſome Surfeit with Meat and Drink, others are ready to Periſh. You will ſay, Hoſpitality is a Vertue: I anſwer, it is not a Vertue to provoke one another to exceſs, nor to make extraordinary Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the Belly, and thereby put one another out of Power to give ſufficient Wages to Workmen, and relief to the helpleſs: It is mocking God and Men, to call Partiality and Unjuſtice, Drunkenneſs and Gluttony a Vertue, or Luxury and Eſſeminacy no Vice: Invitations and Feaſtings are ſcarce ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceſs: But if he that comes, betwixt Meals, to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96950:33"/>ſee thee, happens then to be Hungry or a Thirſt, thou may'ſt preſent to him a piece of Bread, and a draught of Drink, which will ſuffice if he want it, but there is no neceſſity thou ſhould'ſt eat and drink thy ſelf, and needleſly conſume what others may want; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; that ſuch uncharitable and injurious Good-Fel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowſhips be prevented, they ſhould be puniſhed by the Laws: True Hoſpitality ſhould be known to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in providing for the Deſtiture and Afflicted, taking care of Children and Widows, the Lame and the Blind, the Poor, the Sick, and old Perſons, and being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to give Meat and Drink to thoſe that want it. To that end, Temperance and Frugality ſhould be judged to be indiſpenſibly neceſſary Vertues; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians therefore ſhould be always Frugal and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and ſhould not ſpend the ſuperfluities of their Eſtates in Feaſting and Rioting, as is become ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, inſtead of employing to the beſt Advantage of the Publick what they can ſpare. What more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon than to conſume at a Wedding what might ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently maintain a Family moſt part of the Year; and, for ordinary People, to Spend at a Chriſtening more than they freely beſtow upon the Poor in all their Life? Even at Burials, ſo much is Spent vainly and needleſsly, as would be very advantageous, if put to good uſes: Thus, unneceſſarily creating to themſelves ſo many occaſions of Expences, Men make themſelves poor and unable to do any thing for the Publick, they are always on the Rack for Mony, and they, as it were, neceſſitate themſelves to have recourſe to evil Ways, to injure and cozen others, and in fine to pawn and ruin their Souls, to ſupply to their ſuper-induced Wants. Many are brought to Deſpair by this means; many are thereby affrighted from Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, and having any thing to do with the World, ſeeing it is ſo hard a matter to live in it. For if they keep not up the old expenſive Cuſtoms; if there be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:96950:33"/>not all the coſtly and ridiculous Pomp at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of every one of the Family that goeth out of the World; if there be not Carnivals at Chriſtnings, as well as at Weddings; if the Wife have not finer Cloths and Furniture than her Neighbours; if at every Viſit the Houſe be not metamorphoſed into an Inn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Man is deſpiſed and affronted, and muſt look for no reſt: If he will comply to all this, he is perpetually tormented with care how to find Mony as faſt as it is wanted; he is often in danger of being laid up in Priſon, and in fine, he dieth with the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of leaving his Family deſtitute. This is the miſchief of thoſe Expences, which ſeem innocent in the Eyes of the World; but they ſhould be prevented and hindred by the Fathers of the People. It will be objected, That we read of Saints who have made ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Feaſts, and that our Saviour himſelf aſſiſted at one, in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee.</hi> I anſwer, That infallibly our Saviour approved not of Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, tho' he thought good to be preſent at that Occaſion, to make a Miracle, that his Inſtructions afterwards might bear a greater weight: He had a regard to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Men; and their Capacities to receive his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin: The World had its Childhood and Infancy, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which many things might be winked at, and many allowances made: But now that the Goſpel of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is publickly eſtabliſhed, which exhorts us to <hi>ſell all,</hi> rather than not make a ſufficient Proviſion for them that want our Aſſiſtance; can it be thought licit for any to employ the beſt part of his Eſtate to his Luxury, <hi>to eat and drink, and be drunken,</hi> not caring what ſhare others have of the Neceſſaries and Comforts of Life? That is as little Chriſtian, as it is for rich Men to ſpend their abundance in keeping a great number of Dogs and Horſes. If there were no more Horſes and Dogs kept than are abſolutely neceſſary; if it was not only permitted, but enjoyned to every one to deſtroy all wild
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96950:34"/>Fowls and wild Beaſts, as much as poſſible; there would be more Corn, more Fruit, more Sheep and Cows; and conſequently a better Proviſion for the generality of Men. If this be not regarded, where is Chriſtian Charity? But Men ſeem to be ignorant both of the Publick Intereſt, and of the Duties of Charity; for inſtead of going about to enrich the Publick, and contriving to make every one live eaſily and plentifully, they take all manner of ways to render themſelves uncapable of being helpful to others, indulging a Thouſand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Appetites, and facrificing all they have to their Pleaſure and Vanity, ſo that inſtead of being Rich and able to do much good, they are always Poor and can ſcarce ſupply their own contrived Wants. All thoſe things therefore which are ſuperfluous, and cauſe unneceſſary Expences ſhould be forbidden by expreſs Laws. Even exceſs in Cloths and Apparel ſhould be puniſhable; and thoſe that ſhould bring up their Children and Families in any Pride or Vanity, ſhould be Fined. Thoſe that would wear Rings or Jewels, long Wigs, and longer Garments than is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; and Women that would have Ribbons, high Dreſs, long Trains, and the like, ſhould be Taxed a conſiderable part of their Revenues for it. It is the greateſt Imprudence and Folly, to put eight Yards of Cloth, for inſtance, where Four will do; that which is ſuperfluous, and conſequently needleſs, might be employed to ſome good uſe; what ſerves only one Man, might ſuffice for Two.<note place="bottom">
                           <q>
                              <l>Would you be free? 'tis your chief Wiſh, you ſay,</l>
                              <l>Come on; I'll ſhew thee, Friend, the certain way:</l>
                              <l>If to no Feaſts abroad thou lov'ſt to go,</l>
                              <l>Whil'ſt bount'ous God does Bread at home beſtow;</l>
                              <l>If thou the goodneſs of thy Cloths do'ſt prize</l>
                              <l>By thine own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, and not by others Eyes;</l>
                              <l>If (only ſafe from Weathers) thou canſt Dwell,</l>
                              <l>In a ſmall Houſe, but a convenient Shell;</l>
                              <l>If thou without a Sigh, or Golden Wiſh,</l>
                              <l>Canſt look upon thy Beechen Bowl and Diſh:</l>
                              <l>If in thy Mind ſuch Power and Greatneſs be,</l>
                              <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> King's a Slave compar'd with Thee.</l>
                              <bibl>(Abr. Cowley.)</bibl>
                           </q>
                        </note> But ſome will ſay,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:96950:34"/>thoſe Exceſſes ſhould by no means be hindred; for by them, only, abundance of Artizans get their Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, who ſhould otherwiſe Starve. I Anſwer, the more is the Pity, that in Chriſtian Nations Chriſtians can get their Livelihood by nothing but Exceſſes and Vanities: This ſurely ſhould be amended by a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that will be called Chriſtian. Ways ſhould be found, that Artizans might live in following honeſt Employments, and doing uſeful Works. All thoſe that exerciſe neceſſary Trades, as I have ſaid, ſhould be enabled to get, at leaſt, eighteen Pence, or two Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a Day; and whereas ſome Perſons have not been brought up to laborious Callings, but were uſed to get their Living eaſily by the vain Expences of the Rich, the eaſieſt and neateſt Works, that are uſeful to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, might, as I have obſerved, be reſerved for them: All the Farms might be abated of a third of their uſual Rents, by Law, that many might profitably follow that way of living; And that Farmers might be enabled to let Labourers, Work-men and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans get enough by them: In fine, all Men, of all honeſt Callings, would thus be rich, and live eaſily and plentifully, if, at the ſame time, they were hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, by Chriſtian and wholſom Laws, to ſpend their Mony in Vanities and unneceſſary Things, and were obliged to maintain their Families plainly and honeſtly, and to bring up all their Children to ſome
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:96950:35"/>uſeful work, by which means, knowing of no ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and ſuperinduced Neceſſaries, they ſhould be Maſters of their own Happineſs, without ſlaviſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on other Men. To object, that the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and unneceſſary Expences of Men bring in the Revenue of Governors, were unreaſonable, ſeeing that that might be provided for by better means. If you ſay, that that is eaſie in Common-wealths, where the Charges are not ſo great; I anſwer, that by the Expedients all along mentioned, Princes and Subjects may live plentifully and happily: And then, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that Adepts, or the <hi>Free-gift-Office,</hi> were helpful to a Prince, there would be no colour left for that Objection. But if all Men were not to be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by Laws, from Vanities and unneceſſary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, at leaſt, Miniſters, Lawyers, Phyſicians, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans, Soldiers, and ordinary People ſhould. But if thoſe Nations that are called Chriſtian would be Chriſtian indeed, they ſhould make Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and firſt of all ſhew their good Will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by forbidding at leaſt mere Vanities, as powder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and plating the Hair, wearing of Silver or Gold, and the like, expreſly ſpoken againſt in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Teachers of Humility ſhould not ſuffer themſelves to be called Reverend, Venerable or Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, Fathers nor Rabbi. Were I an Adept, and to negotiate an Agreement, I would propoſe this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, That no Man ſhould be called Lord; for we have one Lord, who is in Heaven. There muſt be diſtinctions among Men, it is ordinarily ſaid. Let it be ſo; there may be the ſame that are now in uſe, without giving the Title of Lordſhip to any Man. A Knight, a Baron, may be called by theſe Names, in ſpeaking to them, and that with as much reſpect, as was ſhewn to a mighty Monarch, when called only by this appllation, <hi>O King,</hi> Dan. 2.4. If I was then to negotiate, I would have it to be expreſly allowed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:96950:35"/>by Law not to uſe Compliments, and particularly not to pull off the Hat, (ſeeing that by theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies ſo great a reſpect of Perſons has been had, to the humbling and mortifying of the Poor, ſome of whom have the greateſt merit, and deſerve the moſt Reſpect;) and, eſpecially, to ſay <hi>Thou</hi> to any Perſon, ſeeing we ſay it to God himſelf. No Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould wear Liveries, that making too great a difference between Men, and all Chriſtians profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be Fellow-Servants to the ſame Maſter. Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querading, and diſguiſing of Men ſhould be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And there ſhould be ſevere Laws made againſt all obſcenity and immodeſty. All Women ſhould even be obliged to wear Handkerchiefs cloſe to their Necks, under conſiderable Penalties. For if we would have a Reformation in the weighty Matters, the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Things ſhould not be neglected. This ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſhew you what Conditions I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>When that Philoſopher comes, who is to come in the Spirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> as your Chymical Books do promiſe, probably he will thus reform ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>So Adepts ſay; and then, poſſibly, will be again fulfilled, in this regard, that Saying, That God chuſeth the fooliſh, the weak and baſe Things of the World, Things which are deſpiſed, and even Things which are not, that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27, 28, &amp; 29.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Except God be pleaſed to intervene, it is to be feared, in the Diſpoſition the generality of Men are in, neither <hi>Elias</hi> nor the Adepts would be welcome to reform the World: Far from it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>When Men come into the other World, my deareſt Friend, they will be horribly aſhamed of that Diſpoſition. To the juſt Tribunal of God, then, wiſe Men will cite them: They will then wiſh they
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96950:36"/>had never injured Vertue. O God, thou wilt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect thy People, and bleſs thine Inheritance! Thou wilt ſend down Fire from Heaven, and conſume thine Enemies! Thou wilt exemplarily puniſh thoſe that moleſt thy Servants, and hate thy Name!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>As things are now, do you think it actually poſſible for a Nation publickly to prepare a Houſe for the Adepts, in caſe there be ſuch Men?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Why not? Do we not find ſeveral Patents granted here, openly, to the ſtudiers of this Art, by <hi>Henry</hi> VI. with the conſent of the Parliament, as you may ſee in a Book of <hi>William Prynn,</hi> called, <hi>Aurum Reginae,</hi> p. 131. <hi>&amp;c. Ex. Rot. Pat. An.</hi> 24 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>m.</hi> 14. <hi>Ex. Rot. Pat. An.</hi> 34 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>m.</hi> 7. <hi>Per ipſum Regem, Auctoritate Parliamenti?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray, deſcribe particularly how you would have ſuch a Houſe to be built.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>That muſt be at another opportunity, if you pleaſe: It is now time for me to take my leave of you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>If there are Adepts in the World, are you not your ſelf one of them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I am no Adept, I aſſure you; tho' that Queſtion be not to be asked by a good Man, for if it were to be anſwered by every Body, an Adept could not be hid. As for me, I do not ſo much as work for the Elixir, and hardly deſerve the name of an Artiſt in the very beginnings of Chymiſtry. I ſeek indeed ſome leſſer Remedies, and would be glad to find <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and Van-<hi>Helmont</hi>'s Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſt, and the way to draw Gold out of Silver, and Silver out of Lead, with ſome profit. But whether I ſhall ever ſucceed, God only knows. I have heard of ſome Men, who pretended to cure moſt Diſtempers without the Elixir; and I know ſome who aſſert, That Silver contains much more Gold, and Lead much more Silver than is ordinarily believed, and that there is a Way to open thoſe Metals, to make
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:96950:36"/>them yield what they contain, without which open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that which is moſt perfect flieth away with the imperfect.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Before we part, pray tell me what you think of the Duties of Adepts to their Friends and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; for you have not ſpoken much of that: Don't you eſteem that they are obliged to expreſs ſenſibly their gratitude to them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>No doubt of it; and Adepts know that, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than we: We ought to be willing to leave that wholly to them, and be ready to do them freely all the Service we can; for, to do them the meaneſt Services, is a greater honour than we deſerve, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if we profeſs our ſelves to be their Diſciples, and deſire to become, one day, Adepts our ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the chief Duties of thoſe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to become Adepts, or at leaſt the particular Friends of Adepts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Moderation and Secreſie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>That's a little too general.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, as touching Secreſie, the ſtudiers of the Art ſhould let no Body, if poſſible, know that they work, to be ſure, not what they work upon; and then an Adept may hope that they may be able to keep his Counſel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But what if they want help, and do deſign to work with ſome Partners; or if they have a Wife and Children, Brothers and Siſters, or ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Friends with them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>If they have ſuch a Family, they muſt either altogether hide from them what they deſign to do, or elſe they muſt bind them by the moſt ſacred Oaths not to be talkative or inquiſitive, and if they have ſome Faith in the Art, to live modeſtly and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, as the Friends of Artiſts ought to do, and to employ to good and vertuous uſes, what ſhall be given them in caſe of ſucceſs: They may expreſs
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96950:37"/>this Covenant fully in all its Branches, and make them of their Family write and ſign it, to oblige them to it, and to put them often in mind of their Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And after all, they ſhould do every-thing as ſecretly as if none of thoſe Meaſures had been taken; and in caſe they happened to ſucceed in any thing, they ſhould not preſently let any of their Family know ſo much, but keep it private as long as poſſible. For my part, were I in thoſe Circumſtances, and had I ſuch a Family, I would obſerve all that I have ſaid. I would oblige my Wife and Children, my Brothers and Siſters, to go plain as the Quakers, to ſee no Company but what I liked; to forbear play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at any Game, Dancing, at leaſt with Perſons of different Sexes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I would oblige them to keep ſuch hours, in the Houſe, as I thought beſt; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no Viſits before two, nor after ſix of the Clock in the Afternoon, and not to make the Buſineſs of Viſits to conſiſt in eating and drinking without need; to accuſtom themſelves to inſtruct their Servants ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly in the Chriſtian Religion, and to take delight in a grave and uſeful Converſation: I would make them promiſe, that, in caſe I ſucceeded, and gave them a conſiderable Sum, they ſhould not alter this way of living; they ſhould not uſe any Oſtentation; they ſhould not conſume their abundance in keeping a dainty Table; they ſhould not give any Liveries to any Servant; they ſhould educate their Children, and oblige them to live after the ſame way, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them up plainly, without any Vanity and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity, accuſtoming them to ſerve others, uſing them to work and labour, and cauſing them to learn ſome Trade, that they might not altogether depend upon their Eſtate, but might be able, in caſe of neceſſity, to live of themſelves; they ſhould teach them to fear God, to love other Men as their Fellow-Creatures, and to have always before their Eyes that all Men,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:96950:37"/>in moſt reſpects, are equal, without which there can be no Charity: But in the firſt place I would make them oblige themſelves, that they ſhould not enquire, nor ſeek to know what I did; and in caſe they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to perceive and diſcover the leaſt thing, or any part of it, that they ſhould ever keep it inviolably ſecret: And, in fine, I would make many uſeleſs Operations, and work often upon ſome wrong Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, purpoſedly to blind, and to try them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>But what if you were to work with ſome Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>I would not chuſe, for that, young and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet Perſons; nor would do like ſome People, who tell every Body what they deſign to go upon, becauſe they hope they may be a little helpful to them; theſe Men, how erroneous ſoever their Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies be, are as much guilty as if they had proſtituted and made publick the Elixir; for that which they divulge may be the way to make it, for ought they know: They ſhould conſider how enormous, and of what fatal conſequence is their Guilt, and that they ſhall be anſwerable to God for all the Miſchiefs that may enſue: They ſhould not forget how much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie Adepts require. I wiſh they knew, what I have been told, That an Adept, not long ſince, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing himſelf to a Perſon in Town, to whom he ſhewed his Powder, offered to communicate to him the Secret, on no other condition than that he ſhould ſacredly promiſe to chuſe to die rather than reveal to any Body the leaſt thing concerning it, about which the other making ſome difficulties, the Adept left him, and taught him nothing. They might remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what honeſt and pious <hi>Daulton</hi> did.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>He ſaid, Lord Jeſu, bleſſed Thou be.</l>
                        <l>Methinks I have been too long from Thee.</l>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:96950:38"/>
                        <l>A Science Thou gaveſt me with full great charge,</l>
                        <l>Which I have kept without out-rage.</l>
                        <l>I found no Man yet apt thereto,</l>
                        <l>To be mine Heir when I am go:</l>
                        <l>Wherefore (ſweet Lord) now I am fain</l>
                        <l>To reſign this Thy Gift to Thee again.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Norton</hi> giveth a reaſon of this Secreſie:</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>—This Sience muſt ever ſecret be,</l>
                        <l>The cauſe whereof is this as ye may ſee;</l>
                        <l>If one evil Man had hereof all his Will,</l>
                        <l>All Chriſtian Peace he might haſtily ſpill;</l>
                        <l>And with his Pride, he might pull down</l>
                        <l>Rightful Kings and Princes of Renown:</l>
                        <l>Wherefore the Sentence of Peril and Jeopardy,</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Teacher reſteth dreadfully.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Thus we ſee Sir <hi>George Ripley</hi> making theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions with <hi>Edward</hi> IV. the which probably were never agreed unto:</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>That to your ſelf ye ſhall keep it full ſecretly,</l>
                        <l>And only it uſe as may be to God's Pleaſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thomas Charnock</hi> had theſe Terms offered, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon him by his Maſter:</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Will you with me to morrow be content,</l>
                        <l>Faithfully to receive the bleſſed Sacrament,</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Oath that I ſhall here you give,</l>
                        <l>For ne Gold ne Silver, as long as you live,</l>
                        <l>Neither for love you bear towards your Kin,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet to no great Man, Preferment to win;</l>
                        <l>That you diſcloſe the Secret that I ſhall you teach,</l>
                        <l>Neither by Writing, nor by no ſwift Speech.</l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:96950:38"/>
                     <p>The like Caution ſhould be uſed with all Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the work, in caſe any were taken, and ſuch Counſels and Exhortations, as thoſe of <hi>Bloom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> ſhould be often given them, to perſuade them to Moderation, and confirm them in all Piety and Vertue.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Be you Holy therefore, Sober, Honeſt and Meck,</l>
                        <l>Love God and your Neighbour, to the Poor be not unkind;</l>
                        <l>Overcome Satan, God's Glory ſee you ſeek;</l>
                        <l>My Son, be gentle to all Men as a Friend;</l>
                        <l>Fatherleſs and Widow have alway in thy Mind;</l>
                        <l>Th' innocent love as Brothers, the wicked eſchew;</l>
                        <l>Let Falſhood and Flattery go, leſt thou it rue.</l>
                        <l>Devoutly ſerve God, call daily for his Grace,</l>
                        <l>Worſhip him in Spirit with Heart contrite and pure,</l>
                        <l>In no wiſe let Satan thy Prayers deface:</l>
                        <l>Look thou be ſtedfaſt in Faith, and truſt moſt ſure,</l>
                        <l>Lay up Treaſure in Heaven which ever ſhall endure.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Theſe Words of <hi>Iſaac Holland,</hi> in his <hi>Work of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> ſhould alſo be often remembred. <q>If God give you this Stone, look diligently to it, that you keep your ſelf from offending God, that you make not this Stone on Earth to be your Heaven; govern and rule your ſelf to God's Glory and to the Comfort of poor People, that God's Praiſe may be augmented, to the Defence of the Chriſtian Religion, and to the Relief of poor exil'd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. I tell you, My Child, if you uſe it otherwiſe, God will leave you here a little while to your own Will, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he will ſpeedily ſend a Puniſhment; either you ſhall be ſtruck dead, or die by a Fall, or die ſome other ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death, and go Body and Soul to Hell, and be damned eternally. <hi>And in another place,</hi> Do not undertake this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Work, if you find your ſelf in deadly Sins, or that your Intent be otherwiſe than to God's Glory, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96950:39"/>thoſe Things which I taught you before. I tell you truly, you may ſee the Work, but I am certain you ſhall never accompliſh it, (not enjoy it,) God will order it ſo, one Diſaſter or other will happen.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>After all, things ought to be ſo ordered by a skilful Artiſt, that his Partners or Fellow-Work-men, if he take any, may know little or nothing of the Proceſs, and be bound upon Oath never to work ſeparately from him in this Art, nor to communicate, any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ways, to any Perſon, any thing they ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, or ſhall think to have diſcovered of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that is, of his manner of working, or of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials he worketh upon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>If there was no ſuch thing as the Philoſopher's Stone, as I know not whether there be, yet I find what you have ſaid in this Converſation ſo uſeful, that I would have you publiſh it in the form of a Dialogue: But you muſt endeavour to expreſs it po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litely and neatly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe that will not receive profitable Truths, becauſe offered to them, as it were, in earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, are not worthy of the Preſent, no more than one that ſhould refuſe a bag full of Diamonds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Bag were courſe and ragged. I will never ſtand to paint and verniſh what in it ſelf is excellent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh you the opportunity of working, and good ſucceſs, if there be any thing in the Hermetick Philoſophy: I believe a very good uſe might be made of it. Pray, give me the riming, Latin Verſes, which you ſpoke of, the laſt time we were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ille ſed qui capiet per hanc rem Honores,</l>
                        <l>Antiquos Mores mutabit in meliores.</l>
                        <l>Iſte cumque venerit, Regnum reformabit,</l>
                        <l>Virtutibus &amp; Moribus, &amp; Exemplum dabit,</l>
                        <l>Sempiternum Regibus; Plebs tunc jubilabit,</l>
                        <l>Et, mutuo ſe diligens, laudes Deo dabit.</l>
                     </q>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96950:39"/>
                  <p>THE SUMMARY OF SOME CONFERENCES OF A Student in Chymiſtry WITH AN ARTIST.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96950:40"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96950:40"/>
                  <head>Advertiſement.</head>
                  <p>ALtho', I confeſs, I do not believe any part of the Hermetick Philoſophy to be infallible, I eſteem nevertheleſs that the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Summary of the Converſations of two Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts may be acceptable to divers, and may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be of ſome uſe, tho' it be given but as a Chymical Fiction; becauſe it makes way for the Negotiation of Artiſts, and ſhews how it may be managed. It is not impoſſible that there ſhould be ſuch Men as Adepts; and if there are any, it were extremely to be wiſhed that they might be perſuaded to communicate themſelves, which is here endeavoured, and the way made plain for it. If there be a reality in any Branch of the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick Art, as poſſibly there may, the means to attain to the Knowledge thereof is to ſeek and work for't. It ſeems that, at leaſt, ſome good Remedies may be found, if nothing more. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Perſons that are able did join to that end ſome part of what they can well ſpare, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that in time ſomething would be found that might be uſeful to the Society, if there be any thing in Chymiſtry. And if a good Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was aſſured to Adepts by Perſons of known Probity, ſurely they would diſcover themſelves to them, (if there be any ſuch Men in the
<pb facs="tcp:96950:41"/>World,) and become beneſicial to their Fellow-Creatures, more than they have been hitherto. It cannot then be impertinent for a Man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Houſe, ſo as that it may be acceptable to ſome Adept. That will be of little preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, if there are no Adepts; but if there are ſuch Philoſophers as thoſe actually in being, ſuch an Invitation is likely to have its effect, and the advantage of that would be unſpeakable. That therefore which would coſt little, might be of the greateſt benefit in the World, if <hi>Faith</hi> was publickly promis'd <hi>to Adepts,</hi> and a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration made for their Reception. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fair and equal might be crown'd with ſucceſs and obtain the Divine Bleſſing, whereas the ways of Violence hitherto deſign'd by Great Men in ſuch caſes, are attended with a curſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly ſhall be puniſhed as the greateſt Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in Hell.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96950:41"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE</hi> Summary of the Conferences.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Artiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay, it is not only poſſible to draw Gold out of Silver, and Silver out of Lead with ſome Profit, but it is more than probable that it may be done by the Method which I imagin. As for the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of drawing Silver out of Lead, every common Refiner can teſtify it, tho' they do it without any Art, and therefore loſe the greateſt part of the Silver; for this Silver, beſides that it is as yet ſcarce fully perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and digeſted, is ſo intimately united with its Mother, (Lead) a moſt volatile Body and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed in the Fire, that it neceſſarily flieth away with it, except it be ſomewhat more ripened by an artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Preparation and Compoſition, and the Pores of the Lead be opened, to facilitate the Separation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the examen of cupelling or violent melting. And as for drawing Gold out of Silver, (which, it ſelf, is an immature Sol,) <hi>Roger Bacon</hi> tells ye, That <hi>the Gold is not brought into it by the Spirits,</hi> or any of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients with which the Silver is prepared, <hi>but every kind of Silver hath (at leaſt) one Ounce of Gold in eight Ounces.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Student.</speaker>
                     <p>Granting this, yet the chief difficulty ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, how to prepare the Silver and Lead a-right, which depends upon Experience; have you ever made any trial of it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Some things may be highly credible and in ſome meaſure certain, without an actual Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Every one hath not the conveniency and means of making many Experiments. But I have ſo ſtrong Reaſons to believe I am in the right Method, that I eſteem it worth any Man's while to try it. They that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96950:42"/>will be at no pains nor coſt, tho' they can afford it, are not like (nor deſerve) ever to find any thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you be pleas'd to ſhew the Reaſons, which you think ſo credible and certain?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>That cannot be, without divulging the Secret.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>If you entruſt me with it, I will aſſure you it ſhall go no farther; and in caſe I find the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to try it, and your Proceſs prove ſucceſsful, you ſhall have all reaſonable ſhare in the Profits: That's all I can do, and it ſeems very fair, ſeeing your ſelf acknowledge you have no experimental Demonſtration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>I have not told you expreſly ſo much. Time hath been that I had Means and Opportunity to make Chymical Experiments; but if I had made this, I would not be forward to tell it; I only ſay, That by my Experiments and Study I find it credible, that by a certain Method which I imagin, Gold may be drawn out of Silver, and Silver out of Lead with Proſit. But whether or no I know any thing, or may abſolutely be miſtaken, I do not deſign to divulge what I think ſhould be kept ſecret. What aſſurance have I of your Secreſie; or to what purpoſe ſhould I communicate to you any of my Thoughts, if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help me in any thing, and if you will be at no charge?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>Tho' I cannot do much my ſelf, yet I might find ſome Friends that ſhould be able, and would be willing to be at ſome coſt, in caſe of a Reality or high Probability: And as for Secreſie, you may bind me to it by the ſtrongeſt Ties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you ſacredly promiſe, as you will anſwer, it to Almighty God, to keep the Secret inviolable, and to ſeek to diſcover no more than I ſhall think fit expreſly to tell you; will you ſubſcribe to this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>I will; and I do hereby engage my ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, that I will not any way reveal any thing that you ſhall tell me concerning Chymiſtry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96950:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>But what Friends are thoſe, whoſe Ability and Aſſiſtance you would make uſe of; and what Conditions would you make with them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>I would addreſs my ſelf to none but Men of known Probity and Piety, and of ſufficient Abilities: And the Conditions I would propoſe, ſhould, firſt, be Secreſie, on their part, and to make the neceſſary Advances, and I would aſſure them a good Intereſt for their Mony.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you mean with your Propoſal of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie; would you tell 'em every thing you knew?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>No; but I would require of them not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge the Agreement betwixt them and me, for the Reaſons which you may ſuppoſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſhould you know if they were Men of Vertue and Integrity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>I would addreſs my ſelf to none but thoſe you'd approve of, your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhould then deal only with ſuch, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of taking any Intereſt for their Mony, would rather make you a Penſion, and would be content to beſtow upon the Poor what Profit they might expect: But if at the term of two or three Years you were not able to re-imburſe them, (in caſe they were to make conſiderable Advances,) what ſhould be done?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>They might aſſure to them what I had in the World. But I would not have any Dealings but with thoſe that were able and willing to venture ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. There is always hazard and uncertainty in Chymical Affairs, and it cannot be otherwiſe, unleſs ſo many Experiments had been made as amounted to a Demonſtration; but before that be arriv'd unto, an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Man is often beggered, ſo that he cannot do in this buſineſs what he would and what another may. It is poſſible (certainly, notwithſtanding all the Abuſes that have been made of this Truth,) that one have the right Theory, and yet fail often in ſmall Circumſtances, as all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96950:43"/>Philoſophers ſay of themſelves that they have done, tho' they ſaw plainly they were in the right Path. An extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Courage, a great deal of Strength, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Ability in this caſe is neceſſary. For my part, I have for ſome time ſtudied the Writings of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, but have found nothing but expence in that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and never yet could hear of an Adept, nor of any that was grown rich by this means.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſs I have been no luckier than you, as to what concerns Adepts and the Elixir or Philoſophers Stone. But I make no doubt but that we may get a Competency by drawing Silver out of Lead, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Gold out of Silver, if you can but procure us Mony to ſet us up, to furniſh a Houſe and provide other Neceſſaries, and keep us and ſome Servants 'till our Preparations be made and we begin to have ſome Profits, which poſſibly would be in four or five Months time, or there-abouts. Beſides we may probably find out ſome extraordinary good Remedies, which in time may be very profitable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh things may ſucceed according to your Expectation. But if you were pleaſed to give me your Receit, could not I firſt of all try it in little; or if it cannot be done except we have a whole Houſe and many Conveniencies for the purpoſe, would it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to communicate the Secret to ſome rich Man that were vertuous and diſcreet?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Go not ſo faſt; you are much too haſty. You don't yet know any thing of the Receit your ſelf; do not talk already of communicating it. I muſt tell ye, I never deſign'd to reveal more than the fourth part of it to you, tho' by the Converſations we have had to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſince our acquaintance, and the inquiries I have made, I have tried and found you to have diſcretion and the fear of God, without which you ſhould have been no Friend nor Partner for me; and I will not diſcover more than ſo much to any Man, for fear of the worſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96950:43"/>The World is wicked and unworthy; and Secrets of this nature ought by no means to be proſtituted and publiſhed. There are few good and deſerving Men; two or three of thoſe (when they are well known) may be made choice of, to be entruſted, under the Seal of Secreſie, that one preparing one thing, and another ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ingredient, it be not even in any one's power to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge the whole Proceſs. But if there be any Gains to be made, it were incongruous to make any rich Man partaker of it; for if he be vertuous, he is more than contented with his abundance, and if he be not reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it were unphiloſophical to deal with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>But vertuous, rich Men might be moſt able to do much good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>If they be honeſt, let 'em do what is incumbent on them; let them enable poor Artiſts to be beneficial, without ſeeking to know their Art, which God has not thought fit to commit to them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>After all, ſuppoſing you certainly had a way to make ſome Proſits by Chimiſtry and mixing and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of Metals, what danger or miſchief could there be to communicate the Receit to ſeveral Perſons of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ranks; for if they were never ſo bad, yet would they not, think you, keep your Secret for their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; and if they were good Men, would they not do it out of Conſcience and Religion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>You talk like a raw Artiſt and one of no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. If they were rich, they would not work themſelves, but employ others, and ſo the order of the World might be deſtroyed, the Art in a ſhort time being common. If they be good Men, they may be impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and not ſecret enough; How few good Men but would leave the Art to their Families, tho' it ought to be communicated neither for love nor kindred ſake! And if they be wicked, it would be a heinous Sin to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich them by Philoſophy, and enable them to commit their Riots, and trample under foot the reſt of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96950:44"/>World. In fine, that the generality of Men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, is reaſon enough not to divulge ſuch a Secret. How baſe and unjuſt are moſt Men, who would make no ſcruple to perſecute the Servants and Children of God; and how prophane and impious who would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt Heaven and fight againſt God, to be, in ſpight of him, maſters of his Secrets! But, I remember, you have ſometime conſidered theſe things and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned them; How have you forgotten 'em?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm glad to ſee you are in the ſame Mind with me; I have the more Hopes of your Chymical Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and think you are even qualified for the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of Adepts. But, ſeeing you will not wholly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt me with your Proceſs, before we undertook it in the great, could you not, your ſelf, try it in little?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>It cannot be done in leſs Time, nor with much leſs Charge at firſt, (becauſe of the Rooms, Utenſils and other Conveniences that ſhould be neceſſary) than if we made a greater quantity together: And I need no Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment to be aſſured that I am in the right; for I have abundant reaſon to be conſident of that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>If I ſaw ſuch a probability, I would borrow Mony at eight <hi>per Cent.</hi> to provide all Neceſſaries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Do what you will. I deſire nothing in hand. Get but thoſe things which it will be your ſhare to prepare; fit your ſelf to make thoſe Preparations, and furniſh a Houſe, where I may have Lodgings and Entertainment about half a year after it is ready, that is, as ſoon as the Profits begin to be perceived, half of which by Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall belong to me. Let there be a Laboratory, in the Houſe, peculiar to my ſelf, and a ſpare Room, well furniſhed, in caſe ſome Adept in time will pleaſe to come to us; for that is my greateſt aim and deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſtrange that no Adept will communicate himſelf. Could not an Adept addreſs himſelf to the chief Paſtors, or the States and ſupream Governor of a Land? Surely, the anointing would be reſpected.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96950:44"/>Something ſhould be tried, to do good to the World. However, could not one communicate himſelf to ſome honeſt private Man, and a vertuous and induſtrious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, ſuch as your ſelf?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Hitherto Men have not courted Adepts, nor been civil to them; far from that, they ſeem to have been under Perſecution every where, and in danger of every Body. Therefore we cannot tell what we would do our ſelves, were we Adepts: Such a one always runs a hazard, when he diſcovers himſelf. By length of time, being approved vertuous and ſecret, and juſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſers of that which Providence has committed, there may be, perhaps, ſome hopes. But the generality of Men look upon Adepts as mean Rogues, which do not deſerve the leaſt Regard, and whoſe ſafe living in the Society, is not worth the being provided for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>The more is the Pity. I do not therefore blame Adepts for being cautious. But I think there may be over-doing in any thing. What hurt can there be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal ſomething to one that is known to be honeſt, and is under the Obligation of Secreſie?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>True. But every one will be free, and will take his own Time and the fitteſt Opportunity. I am in the ſame diſpoſition my ſelf. When I ſee you have a Houſe ready, and ſome Conveniences, I ſhall diſcover to you more of my Thoughts. Now I'll tell you, and I don't care if all the World know it, that if we do any thing, we may work theſe Materials: Lead, ſuppoſe, 12 <hi>l.</hi> Iron, 1 <hi>l.</hi> Red Copper, 2 <hi>l.</hi> Antimony, 8 <hi>l.</hi> Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, 2 Ounces; Gold, 1 Ounce; choice, River-Sand, 10 <hi>l.</hi> Sea-Stones, 6 <hi>l.</hi> Vitriol, 2 <hi>l.</hi> Marchaſſites, 4 <hi>l.</hi> Cinaber, 5 <hi>l.</hi> adding ſome other things: Something muſt be uſed which hath an extraordinary opening Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; the Tincture of many Ingredients muſt be drawn, which can be drawn but in little; you muſt make good Spirit of Wine and Spirit of Vinegar; you muſt dry, at a gentle Fire, in a cloſe Veſſel, during the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96950:45"/>ſpace of four and twenty Hours, ſomething that I ſhall give you; you muſt join ſome Tinctures according to a due Method and Pondus, and then, following my Directions, I believe we ſhall find ſome Profit, and, it may be, ſome good Remedies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stud.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe Experiments are for the great Men of the World, or thoſe at leaſt who have a conſiderable Sum of Mony to ſpare every Year, (two hundred Pounds perhaps) and can calmly hazard it, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent if nothing come on't, generouſly venturing that for the good of Mankind, reſolving to make a good uſe of it in caſe of ſucceſs, and otherwiſe being able to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain the loſs, and actually bearing it like Philoſophers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Men have other things to buſie their Heads with, and generally Truth is left deſtitute and unregarded. 'Tis to be feared it will always be ſo. Howbeit, by the Entertainment which Adepts Friends find, Adepts may judge what they are to expect: And Wiſdom will be juſtified by her Children, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be. But thoſe that are experienced, are of opinſon that the Art requires no very great Sum. All that I deſire is, that I may have the opportunity to invite to me, and to entertain and protect ſome Adept, which I proteſt, before God and Men, I would do with moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Fidelity. And I conclude with this Profeſſion, That I hold it the greateſt madneſs, as well as the greateſt injuſtice in the World to ſeek to diſcover them, to injure them or offer them any violence, and thereby heap Wrath againſt the day of Wrath; and I eſteem it infinitely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable, either never to poſſeſs their Medicinal Treaſures, or to obtain the ſame from them by their good Will, and the divine Grace: In fine, I am verily apt to believe, that by the Means and upon the Conditions I have mention'd, ſome Adept e're it be long will communicate himſelf, if Men will publickly premiſe to protect Adepts, and to maintain them in their full Liberty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96950:45"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
